<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1321 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1321.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5905 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7384 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7384.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7821 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7821.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7822 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7822.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8039 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8039.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8573 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8573.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8877 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8877.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8915 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8915.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9523 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9523.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9748 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9748.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9769 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9769.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-ntp-ntpv5-07" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>Network Time Protocol Version 5</title>

    <author fullname="Miroslav Lichvar" initials="M." surname="Lichvar">
      <organization>Red Hat</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mlichvar@redhat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tal Mizrahi" initials="T." surname="Mizrahi">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <email>tal.mizrahi.phd@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2025" month="Oct" day="16"/>

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>NTP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Network Time Protocol (NTP) is a widely deployed protocol that
        allows hosts to obtain the current time of day from time servers. This
        document specifies version 5 of the protocol (NTPv5), which adopts a
        client-server model as its sole mode of operation. Legacy operational
        modes supported in earlier versions have been removed to improve
        protocol robustness and clarity. While this specification defines the
        protocol used for time distribution, it does not define the algorithms
        or heuristics employed by clients to determine or adjust their local
        time.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Network Time Protocol (NTP) is a widely used protocol that
        enables hosts to synchronize their clocks over packet-switched,
        variable-latency data networks. Time is distributed hierarchically,
        beginning with primary time servers, often synchronized to Coordinated
        Universal Time (UTC) via external sources such as GNSS, and propagating
        through a network of clients. These clients may themselves act as
        servers for downstream systems, forming a time distribution tree. To
        enhance reliability, stability, and accuracy, clients can query
        multiple servers concurrently and apply local algorithms to select and
        combine time sources.</t>

      <t>This document specifies version 5 of the protocol (NTPv5), which
        defines only the on-the-wire protocol used for time exchange. It does
        not cover client-side algorithms such as source selection, filtering of
        time measurements, or clock discipline. These aspects are considered
        out of scope.</t>

      <t>NTPv5 adopts a simplified client-server model as its sole operational
        mode. For security and robustness, legacy modes from previous versions,
        such as symmetric active, symmetric passive, broadcast, control, and
        private modes, have been removed. Only client and server modes are
        retained in this version.</t>

      <t>To support optional features and future extensibility, NTPv5 makes use
        of extension fields. This document defines several such fields, which
        may be included in protocol messages to convey additional information
        beyond the core header.</t>

      <t>NTPv5 supports secure operation through two possible mechanisms
        originally defined for NTPv4. The first is the <xref
        target="RFC8573">NTP Message Authentication Code (MAC)</xref>
        mechanism, which provides basic message integrity. The second is <xref
        target="RFC8915">Network Time Security (NTS)</xref>, which offers
        stronger security guarantees, including server authentication, replay
        protection, and secure key establishment.</t>

      <t>This specification also introduces a feature aimed at improving
        synchronization accuracy. The Correction Extension Field allows clients
        and servers to communicate variable delays introduced by intermediate
        network devices such as switches and routers.</t>

      <t>Backward compatibility is supported through version negotiation. A
        server that implements multiple protocol versions responds using the
        same version as the client's request, provided that version is
        supported.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions">
      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>Abbreviations used in this document:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="11" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="MAC">Message Authentication Code</t>

          <t hangText="NTP">Network Time Protocol</t>

          <t hangText="NTS">Network Time Security</t>

          <t hangText="NTS-KE">Network Time Security Key Establishment</t>

          <t hangText="ppm">parts per million</t>

          <t hangText="PTP">Precision Time Protocol</t>

          <t hangText="SI">International System of Units</t>

          <t hangText="TAI">International Atomic Time</t>

          <t hangText="TC">Transparent Clock</t>

          <t hangText="UT1">Universal Time 1</t>

          <t hangText="UTC">Coordinated Universal Time</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
          "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
          capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Main Differences Between NTPv5 and NTPv4">
      <t>NTPv5 is very similar to <xref target="RFC5905">NTPv4</xref>. The
        main differences are:

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The protocol specification (this document) describes only the
            on-wire protocol. Filtering of measurements, security mechanisms,
            source selection, clock control, and other algorithms, are out of
            scope.</t>

          <t>For security reasons, NTPv5 drops support for the symmetric
            active, symmetric passive, broadcast, control, and private modes.
            The symmetric and broadcast modes are vulnerable to replay attacks.
            The control and private modes can be exploited for
            denial-of-service traffic amplification attacks. Only the client
            and server modes remain in NTPv5.</t>

          <t>The NTPv5 message format differs from that of NTPv4. However,
            the Version Number field remains at the same offset in both formats,
            enabling protocol implementations to distinguish between
            the two versions.</t>

          <t>Timestamps are clearly separated from values used as cookies.</t>

          <t>Synchronized server clock is indicated in a separate flag instead
            of the leap indicator.</t>

          <t>NTPv5 messages can be extended only with extension fields. The MAC
            field is wrapped in an extension field to avoid an ambiguity in
            parsing of the NTP message, which was later addressed for NTPv4 in
            <xref target="RFC7822">RFC 7822</xref>.</t>

          <t>Extension fields can be of any length, even indivisible by 4, but are
            padded to a multiple of 4 octets. Extension fields specified for NTPv4
            can be included in NTPv5 messages as specified for NTPv4.</t>

          <t>NTPv5 adds support for timescales other than UTC.</t>

          <t>The NTP era number is exchanged in the protocol, which extends the
            unambiguous time interval from 136 years to about 35000 years.</t>

          <t>NTPv5 adds a flag to clearly identify the use of interleaved mode
            instead of comparing timestamps or cookies. The server's receive
            timestamps do not need to be unique in order to support the
            interleaved mode.</t>

          <t>NTPv5 works with sets of reference IDs to prevent synchronization
            loops over multiple hosts, even if they form over other NTP sources
            than the system peer. Reference IDs have 120 bits instead of 32
            bits to minimize the rate of false positives.</t>

          <t>Resolution of the root delay and root dispersion fields is
            improved from about 15 microseconds to about 4 nanoseconds.</t>

          <t>Clients do not leak information about their clock (e.g.
            timestamps, estimated accuracy).</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Basic Concepts">
      <section anchor="ntp-exchange-sec" title="The NTP Message Exchange">
        <t>An NTP client exchanges messages with one or more NTP servers;
          the client sends a request to each server and the servers send their
          responses back to the client. Both the client and servers measure the
          time of transmission and reception of every message they send and
          receive. The servers provide their timestamps to the client.</t>

        <t>The NTP message exchange is illustrated in <xref
          target="basic-concept-figure"/>, depicting four timestamp
          values:</t>

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>T1 - client's transmit timestamp of the request</t>
          <t>T2 - server's receive timestamp of the request</t>
          <t>T3 - server's transmit timestamp of the response</t>
          <t>T4 - client's receive timestamp of the response</t>
        </list>

        <figure align="center" anchor="basic-concept-figure"
          title="NTP message exchange between client and server">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
          Server         T2   T3
             ------------+----+--------
                        /      \
               request /        \ response       ---> time
                      /          \
             --------+------------+-----
          Client     T1           T4
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The timestamps T1 and T4 are recorded locally by the client and are
          not transmitted over the network. In contrast, the server includes
          timestamps T2 and T3 in its response to the client. As a result, by
          the end of the exchange, the client has access to all four
          timestamps, commonly referred to as a sample.</t>

        <t>The client can use the set of four timestamps to estimate both the
          clock offset relative to the server and the network delay. The
          offset of the server clock relative to the client clock can be
          calculated using Eq. (1), and the two-way delay between the client
          and server can be estimated using Eq. (2).</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
(1)  offset = ((T2 + T3) - (T4 + T1)) / 2
(2)  delay  = |(T4 - T1) - (T3 - T2)|
        ]]></artwork>

        <t>The offset and delay estimates given in the two equations above
          are based on a single timestamp sample. In practice, a client
          typically maintains ongoing estimates of offset and delay by
          aggregating multiple samples collected over several message
          exchanges.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Hierarchical Time Distribution">
        <t>NTP supports a hierarchical time distribution scheme. This hierarchy
          is defined by stratum levels, which indicate the distance from the
          reference time source. Stratum 1 servers are directly synchronized with
          an external reference clock. Servers that synchronize with stratum 1
          servers are classified as stratum 2, and the hierarchy continues in
          this manner.</t>

        <t>An NTP response message contains two fields, root delay and root
          dispersion, which together provide an estimate of the server's time
          error accumulated along the synchronization path.</t>

        <t>Root delay represents the cumulative delay along the path to the
          reference time source used by the primary time server. Each server in
          the synchronization chain adds its own delay estimate based on the
          server it deems most accurate. This estimate includes both the measured
          two-way delay towards the server and any processing delays between the
          timestamping and actual sending or receiving of NTP messages. To
          estimate the potential error caused by asymmetric delays, half of the
          root delay is typically used as a bound on the clock's maximum
          error.</t>

        <t>Root dispersion provides an estimate, in time units, of the maximum
          potential error in the clock due to both the instability of clocks
          along the synchronization path and the variability in NTP measurements.
          Each server in the chain contributes its own dispersion value to the
          cumulative root dispersion. The method for estimating dispersion can
          vary between implementations and often depends on the underlying clock
          model. In a simple model, dispersion may be calculated using a constant
          Dispersion Rate (DR), as shown in Equation (3). The constant DR
          represents a relative frequency error, typically within the range (0,
          1). For instance, a DR value of 0.000015 (15 ppm) is suggested in <xref
          target="RFC5905"/>.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
(3)  dispersion = |T4 - T1| * DR
        ]]></artwork>

        <t>The root distance is defined as the sum of the root dispersion and
          half of the root delay. It represents an estimate of the maximum
          possible time error of the clock, accounting for the assumed clock
          stability and the worst-case scenario of asymmetric network delays.
          Although root distance is not transmitted in NTP messages, it can be
          computed and used by the client to assess the accuracy of each of its
          servers.</t>

        <t>A synchronization loop can occur when clients attempt to synchronize
          with each other--either directly or indirectly through other servers.
          Such loops are undesirable in an NTP network, as they create positive
          feedback cycles that can degrade synchronization stability. To help
          detect and prevent these loops, servers use randomly generated
          reference IDs, which are exchanged in NTP messages as described in
          <xref target="reference-ids-extension-fields"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Leap Seconds">
        <t>An NTPv5 server can distribute time using one of four timescales: UTC,
          TAI, UT1, or leap-smeared UTC. The specific timescale in use is
          indicated by the Timescale field in the NTP message. Of these options,
          UTC and leap-smeared UTC are subject to leap second adjustments.</t>

        <t>A leap second is a one-second adjustment occasionally applied to UTC
          to maintain alignment with solar time. This adjustment can be either
          positive, by inserting an extra second, or negative, by removing one.
          To date, only positive leap seconds have been introduced. Therefore,
          the following discussion focuses on the more common case of a positive
          leap second, though the behavior of a negative leap second can be
          inferred.</t>

        <t>When time is distributed using the UTC timescale, a system clock may
          handle a positive leap second in one of two ways: it may either roll
          back by one second at the end of the leap second, or it may pause,
          holding the same time, for the duration of the leap second, as outlined
          in <xref target="RFC8877"/>. As a result, any NTP message exchange that
          occurs outside of a leap second will yield timestamps that reflect
          server's clock according to the actual UTC time.</t>

        <t>When using the leap-smeared timescale, the system clock is gradually
          slowed down during the leap second and surrounding time intervals,
          allowing the time to smoothly adjust until it aligns with the correct
          value. This adjustment period, known as a leap smear period, can span
          from a few seconds to several hours before, during, and/or after the
          scheduled leap second.</t>

        <t>The Leap Indicator (LI) field in an NTP message signals that a leap
          second is scheduled to occur within the next 14 days.</t>
       </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Data Types">
      <t>NTPv5 uses several data types, all represented in network byte
        order. In addition to signed and unsigned integers, it also has
        the following fixed-point types:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="time32"><vspace/>
            A 32-bit unsigned fixed-point type containing values in seconds. It
            has 4 bits describing the unsigned integral part and 28 bits
            describing the fractional part. The maximum value is
            16 seconds and the resolution is about 3.7 nanoseconds. Note that
            this is different from the 32-bit time format in NTPv4.</t>

          <t hangText="timestamp64"><vspace/>
            A 64-bit unsigned fixed-point type containing a timestamp specified
            in seconds. It has 32 unsigned
            integer bits and 32 fractional bits. It spans an interval of about
            136 years and has a resolution of about 0.23 nanoseconds. It can be
            used in different timescales. In the UTC timescale, the timestamp
            is the value 2272060800 added to the number of SI seconds since
            1 Jan 1972, excluding leap second adjustments. The value 2272060800
            is the assumed number of seconds between 1 Jan 1900 and 1 Jan 1972.
            Timestamps in the TAI timescale are the same except they include
            leap seconds and an extra 10-second offset for the original
            difference between TAI and UTC in 1972, when leap seconds were
            introduced. One interval covered by the type is called an NTP era.
            The era starting at the epoch is era number 0, the following era is
            number 1, and so on. A timestamp that has a value of 0 indicates
            an unknown or invalid timestamp (in any NTP era).</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Some fields use a logarithmic scale, where an 8-bit signed integer
        represents the rounded log2 value of seconds. For example, a log2 value
        of 4 represents 2^4 (2 to the power of 4, 16) seconds, or a log2 value
        of -2 represents 2^-2 (0.25 seconds).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Message Format">
      <t>NTPv5 servers and clients exchange messages as UDP datagrams. Clients
        send requests to servers and servers send them back responses. The
        server's UDP port in NTP messages is 123, as assigned by IANA. The
        client's UDP port can be any number consistent with the local policy. The
        format of the UDP payload is shown in Figure <xref format="counter"
          target="message-format"/>.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="message-format"
          title="Format of NTPv5 messages">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|LI | VN  |Mode |    Stratum    |     Poll      |  Precision    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           Root Delay                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Root Dispersion                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Timescale   |      Era      |             Flags             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                        Server Cookie (64)                     +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                        Client Cookie (64)                     +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                      Receive Timestamp (64)                   +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                      Transmit Timestamp (64)                  +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                    Extension Field 1 (variable)               .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                                                               .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                    Extension Field N (variable)               .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Each NTPv5 message has a header containing the following fields:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Leap indicator (LI)"><vspace/>
            A 2-bit field indicating upcoming leap seconds. In requests it is
            always 0. In responses it has one of the following values:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="0: Normal"><vspace/>
                No leap second will be inserted or deleted in the next 14 days,
                or the server is responding in a leap-smeared timescale (i.e.
                the client is not expected to be handling leap seconds).</t>
              <t hangText="1: Insert leap second"><vspace/>
                A leap second will be inserted in the next 14 days at the end
                of the current month.</t>
              <t hangText="2: Delete leap second"><vspace/>
                A leap second will be deleted in the next 14 days at the end of
                the current month.</t>
              <t hangText="3: Unknown"><vspace/>
                The server does not have a time source or other source
                providing information about leap seconds.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t hangText="Version Number (VN)"><vspace/>
            A 3-bit field containing the value 5.</t>

          <t hangText="Mode"><vspace/>
            A 3-bit field containing the value 3 (request) or 4 (response).</t>

          <t hangText="Stratum"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit field containing the stratum of the server. Primary time
            servers have a stratum of 1, their clients have a stratum of 2, and
            so on. The value of 0 indicates an unknown or infinite stratum. In
            requests it is always 0. When 0 in a response, it indicates the
            server was unable or unwilling to provide valid time information.
            Servers advertising a stratum above 15 should not be synchronized
            to, except when the client is explicitly configured to do so by the
            end-user.</t>

          <t hangText="Poll"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit signed integer containing the minimum allowed polling
            interval as a log2 value in seconds. In requests it is always 0. In
            responses it is the server's value that the client is expected to
            follow. This field is valid even when stratum is 0. A value of 127
            indicates the server does not want to hear from the client again.
            Note that the poll value has a different meaning than in NTPv4. It
            supersedes the NTPv4 Kiss-o'-Death (KoD) RATE and DENY codes.</t>

          <t hangText="Precision"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit signed integer containing the precision of the timestamps
            included in the message as a rounded log2 value in seconds. In
            requests, which do not contain any timestamps, it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Root Delay"><vspace/>
            A field using the time32 type. In responses it is the server's root
            delay. In requests it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Root Dispersion"><vspace/>
            A field using the time32 type. In responses it is the server's root
            dispersion. In requests it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Timescale"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit identifier of the timescale. In requests it is the
            requested timescale. In responses it is the timescale of the
            receive and transmit timestamps. Defined values are:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t>0: UTC</t>
              <t>1: TAI</t>
              <t>2: UT1</t>
              <t>3: Leap-smeared UTC</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t hangText="Era"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit unsigned NTP era number corresponding to the receive
            timestamp. In requests it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Flags"><vspace/>
            A 16-bit integer that can contain the following flags:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="0x1: Synchronized"><vspace/>
                In requests it is 0. In responses a value of 1 indicates the
                server's clock is synchronized and the provided timestamps
                can be used by the client for its own synchronization.</t>
              <t hangText="0x2: Interleaved Mode"><vspace/>
                In requests a value of 1 is a request for a response in the
                interleaved mode. In responses a value of 1 indicates the
                response is in the interleaved mode.</t>
              <t hangText="0x4: Authentication NAK"><vspace/>
                In requests it is 0. In responses a value of 1 indicates that
                the server failed to authenticate the request. A server
                setting this bit SHOULD also set the stratum of the message
                to 0.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t hangText="Server Cookie"><vspace/>
            A 64-bit field containing a number generated by the server which
            enables the interleaved mode. In requests it is 0, or a copy of the
            server cookie from the last response.</t>

          <t hangText="Client Cookie"><vspace/>
            A 64-bit field containing a random number generated by the client.
            Responses contain a copy of the field from the corresponding
            request, which allows the client to verify that the responses
            are related to the requests.</t>

          <t hangText="Receive Timestamp"><vspace/>
            A field using the timestamp64 type. In requests it is always
            0. In responses it is the time when the request was received by
            the server. The
            timestamp corresponds to the end of the reception.</t>

          <t hangText="Transmit Timestamp"><vspace/>
            A field using the timestamp64 type. In requests it is always
            0. In responses it is the server's time denoting the beginning of
            the transmission of a
            response to the client. Which response it refers to depends
            on the selected mode (basic or interleaved). See <xref
            target="measurement-modes">Measurement Modes</xref> for detail.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The header has 48 octets, which is the minimum length of a valid NTPv5
        message. A message can contain optional extension fields (zero or more).
        The maximum length is not specified, but the length MUST be divisible
        by 4 octets.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Extension Fields">
      <t>The format of NTPv5 extension fields is shown in Figure <xref
          format="counter" target="extension-field"/>.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="extension-field"
          title="Format of NTPv5 extension fields">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|             Type              |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                           Data (variable)                     .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Each extension field has a header which contains a 16-bit type and
        16-bit length. The length is in octets and it includes the header. The
        minimum length is 4, i.e. an extension field does not have to contain
        any data. If the length is not divisible by 4, the extension field is
        padded with zeros to the smallest multiple of 4 octets in order to
        align the next extension field in the message. The length excludes this
        message-level padding, but includes any potential padding specified as
        a part of the specific extension field.</t>

      <t>If a request contains an extension field, the server MUST include this
        extension field in the response unless the specification of the
        extension field states otherwise, or the server does not support the
        extension field. If the server excludes one or more extension fields in
        the response, it MUST include a Padding extension field that compensates
        for the excluded fields, making the request and response symmetric in
        length. A client can interpret the absence of an expected
        extension field in a response as an indication that the server does not
        support the extension field.</t>

      <t>Extension fields specified for NTPv4 can be included in NTPv5 messages
        as specified for NTPv4.</t>

      <t>The rest of this section describes extension fields specified for
        NTPv5. Clients are not required to use or support any of these
        extension fields, but servers are required to support the following
        extension fields: Padding, Server Information, Reference IDs Request,
        Reference IDs Response.</t>

      <section title="Draft Identification Extension Field">
        <t>Note to the editors: this section must be removed before final publication.</t>

        <t>This field, with type 0xF5FF, is used to indicate which draft of the specification
          an implementation is based upon. It MUST be included in NTPv5 requests produced
          by an implementation based on a draft of this specification, and MUST NOT be included
          in NTPv5 requests produced by an implementation based on the final version of
          this specification. Server MUST use this field if and only if responding
          to a request containing this field and the server is a draft
          implementation.</t>

        <t>The contents of this field MUST be the full name, including version number, of
          the draft upon which the implementation is based, encoded as an ASCII
          string. If the server string is longer than the client string, the
          server MUST NOT respond in that version to prevent traffic
          amplification.</t>

        <t>A server MUST NOT respond to requests with a draft identification it does not
          recognize. If it responds, it SHOULD respond according to the same
          draft specification as given by the client.</t>

        <t>Note: the content of this field MUST NOT be null-terminated (the
          extension field in the NTP message may need to be padded with up to 3
          octets). When comparing the strings be compared in their full length,
          i.e. a longer string containing a shorter string is not
          sufficient.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Padding Extension Field" anchor="padding-extension-field">
        <t>This field, with type [[TBD]] (draft: 0xF501), can have any length.
          The data field within this extension field SHOULD contain zeros
          and it MUST be ignored by the receiver.</t>

        <t>Servers can use this extension field to pad the response to match
          the length of the request if the response does not contain all
          requested extension fields, or some have a variable length. If the
          request message includes a padding extension, the server can increase
          its length if necessary. If the request message does not include a
          padding extension, the server can add it to the response. Clients can
          include the padding extension in the request message, allowing the
          extension to be used for internal purposes. For instance, an NTP
          client receiving a response message can use this extension field to
          transfer the reception time from a hardware module to a software
          module.</t>

        <t>This field MUST be supported on servers.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Measurement Modes" anchor="measurement-modes">

      <t>At the end of an NTP message exchange, the client has access to four
        timestamps, which it can use to estimate the clock offset and the
        network delay, as described in <xref target="ntp-exchange-sec"/>.</t>

      <t>If the Correction Extension Field is used and the corrections are
        known for both the request and response, a corrected offset and delay
        is calculated:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>offset_c = offset + (Cd - Co) / 2</t>
          <t>delay_c = delay - (Cd + Co - Drx - Dtx) * (1 - FC)|</t>
        </list>

        where

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Co is the Origin Correction from the response to the request
            corresponding to timestamps T1 and T2</t>
          <t>Cd is the Delay Correction from the response corresponding to
            timestamps T3 and T4</t>
          <t>FC is the maximum expected frequency error of devices providing
            the delay corrections (e.g. 100 ppm)</t>
          <t>Drx is the time it took to receive the frame containing the
            response corresponding to T3 and T4</t>
          <t>Dtx is the time it took to transmit the frame containing the
            request corresponding to T1 and T2. If unknown, it SHOULD be set to
            Drx.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The corrected offset and delay MUST NOT be accepted if any of delay_c,
        Co and Cr is negative. The uncorrected delay MUST always be used for
        calculation of the root delay.</t>

      <t>The client can make measurements in the basic mode, or interleaved
        mode if supported on the server. In the basic mode, the transmit
        timestamp in the server response corresponds to the message which
        contains the timestamp itself. In the interleaved mode it corresponds
        to a previous response identified by the server cookie. The
        interleaved mode enables the server to provide the client with a more
        accurate transmit timestamp which is available only after the
        response was formed or sent.</t>

      <t>An example of cookies and timestamps in an NTPv5 exchange using the
        basic mode is shown in Figure <xref format="counter"
        target="basic-exchange"></xref>.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="basic-exchange"
          title="Cookies and timestamps in basic mode">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
Server   t2   t3               t6   t7              t10  t11
    -----+----+----------------+----+----------------+----+-----
        /      \              /      \              /      \
Client /        \            /        \            /        \
    --+----------+----------+----------+----------+----------+--
      t1         t4         t5         t8         t9        t12

    +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+
SC  | 0  |    | s1 |      | 0  |    | s2 |      | 0  |    | s3 |
CC  | c1 |    | c1 |      | c2 |    | c2 |      | c3 |    | c3 |
Rx  | 0  |    | t2 |      | 0  |    | t6 |      | 0  |    |t10 |
Tx  | 0  |    | t3 |      | 0  |    | t7 |      | 0  |    |t11 |
    +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>From the three exchanges in this example, the client would use the
        the following sets of timestamps:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>(t1, t2, t3, t4)</t>
          <t>(t5, t6, t7, t8)</t>
          <t>(t9, t10, t11, t12)</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Client Operation">
      <t>An NTPv5 client can use one or multiple servers. It has a separate
        association with each server. It makes periodic measurements of its
        offset and delay to the server. It can filter the measurements and
        compare measurements from different servers to select and combine the
        best servers for synchronization. It can adjust its clock in order to
        minimize its offset and keep the clock synchronized. These algorithms
        are not specified in this document. The client MAY use the <xref
        target="RFC5905">NTPv4</xref> algorithms, or any more or less advanced
        algorithms optimized for the same or different conditions.</t>

      <t>The client SHOULD respect the minimum allowed polling interval
        provided by the server in the poll field of the last valid response,
        but only up to a reasonable maximum value to limit the impact of
        misconfigurations, bugs, and potential denial-of-service attacks where
        the client would accept a spoofed response. For example, the client
        could limit the accepted minimum interval to 2^15 (about 9 hours) if
        authentication is disabled, or 2^18 (about 3 days) if authentication is
        enabled.</t>

      <t>The polling interval can be adjusted for the network conditions and
        stability of the clock. When polling a public server on Internet, the
        client SHOULD use a polling interval of at least 2^6 (64) seconds,
        increasing in normal conditions up to at least 2^10 (1024) seconds to
        avoid excessive load on the server in case the implementation is used
        on a very large number of systems. On start, the client MAY temporarily
        ignore the server's minimum polling interval and send a burst of up to
        8 requests using an interval of only 2^1 (2) seconds in order to
        make the initial correction of the clock sooner.</t>

      <t>The polling interval SHOULD contain a small random part (e.g. up to 2%
        of the target interval in a uniform distribution) in order to spread
        the load on the server if a large number of identical clients are
        (re)started at the same time.</t>

      <t>Each successful measurement provides the client with an offset, delay
        and dispersion. When combined with the server's root delay and
        dispersion, it gives the client an estimate of the maximum error.</t>

      <t>On each poll, the client:

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Generates a new random cookie.</t>

          <t>Formats a request with necessary extension fields and the fields
            in the header all zero except:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Version is set to 5.</t>

              <t>Mode is set to 3.</t>

              <t>Timescale is set to the timescale in which the client wants to
                operate.</t>

              <t>Flags are set according to the requested mode. The interleaved
                mode flag requests the server to save the transmit timestamp of
                the response and provide the transmit timestamp of a previous
                response corresponding to the server cookie (if not zero).</t>

              <t>Server cookie is set only in the interleaved mode. It is set
                to the server cookie from the last valid response, or zero if
                no such response was received yet or the transmit timestamp of
                that response would no longer be useful to the client (e.g.
                after missing too many responses).</t>

              <t>Client cookie is set to the newly generated cookie.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>Sends the request to the server to the UDP port 123 and captures a
            transmit timestamp for the packet.</t>

          <t>Waits for a valid response from the server and captures a receive
            timestamp. A valid response has version 5, mode 4, client cookie
            equal to the cookie from the request, and passes authentication if
            enabled. The client MUST ignore all invalid responses and accept at
            most one valid response.</t>

          <t>Checks whether the response is usable for synchronization of the
            clock. Such a response has the Synchronized flag set, stratum
            not equal to 0 and not larger than 15 (or a different maximum value
            that the client is configured to accept), root delay and dispersion
            both smaller than
            a specific value (e.g. 16 seconds), and timescale equal to the
            requested timescale. If the response is in a different timescale,
            the client can switch to the provided timescale, convert the
            timestamps if the offset between the timescales is known from the
            Secondary Receive Timestamp Extension Field or other sources, or
            ignore the response.</t>

          <t>Saves the server's receive and transmit timestamps. If the client
            internally counts seconds using a type wider than 32 bits, it
            SHOULD expand the timestamps with the provided NTP era.</t>

          <t>Calculates the offset, delay, and dispersion as specified in
            <xref target="measurement-modes">Measurement Modes</xref>.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>A client which operates as a server for other clients MUST include the
        Reference IDs Request Extension Field in its requests in order to track
        reference IDs of its sources. If the server's set of reference IDs
        contains the client's own reference ID, it SHOULD not select the server
        for synchronization to avoid a synchronization loop. If the client
        is requesting the reference IDs in multiple chunks, it SHOULD NOT
        select the server for synchronization until it received the whole
        set.</t>

      <t>A client which uses multiple servers MUST be able to handle servers
        providing timestamps in different timescales. It can ignore servers not
        using the most common or preferred timescale, or convert them to a
        common timescale if it knows the offsets between them.</t>

      <t>If the client synchronizes its clock to a leap-smeared timescale,
        it MUST NOT apply leap seconds and it SHOULD provide the leap-smeared
        timescale to its own clients if it is a server.</t>

      <t>The client SHOULD periodically (e.g. every two weeks) refresh IP
        addresses of all servers specified by hostname to limit the duration
        when an IP address of a migrated or decommissioned server will still be
        receiving NTP traffic from long-running clients. The client SHOULD
        ignore the TTL value of the DNS record that provided the IP address to
        avoid excessive DNS traffic for pools of NTP servers using a short TTL
        for better load balancing.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Server Operation">
      <t>A server receives requests on the UDP port 123. The server
        MUST support measurements in the basic mode. It MAY support the
        interleaved mode.</t>

      <t>For the basic mode the server does not need to keep any
        client-specific state. For the interleaved mode it needs to save
        transmit timestamps and be able to identify them by a cookie.</t>

      <t>The server maintains its leap indicator, stratum, root delay, and root
        dispersion:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Leap indicator MUST be 0, 1, 2, or 3 if, within the next 14 days,
            no leap second will be applied, a leap second will be inserted, a
            leap second will be deleted, or the server has no information about
            leap seconds respectively.</t>
          <t>Stratum SHOULD be 1 if the server is synchronized to a local
            reference clock, or be one larger than the stratum of the NTP
            server it selected as best for synchronization. It MUST be greater
            than the minimum stratum of all servers selected for
            synchronization, as they provided in their last accepted response,
            or 0 to indicate infinity.</t>
          <t>Root delay MUST be an estimate of the double of the maximum error
            of the server's clock due to asymmetries in the network delay and
            other delays (e.g. timestamping) on the path to the primary time
            source. For a server that is synchronized to other NTP servers, one
            possibility is to set it to the latest measured delay to the server
            it considers best plus the root delay provided in that
            response.</t>
          <t>Root dispersion MUST be an estimate of the maximum error of the
            server's clock from other causes than those covered by root delay,
            e.g. instability of the clock and measurements by which it is
            synchronized. If the server is synchronized to other NTP servers,
            it MUST include root dispersion from one of the servers'
            responses.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The server has a randomly generated 120-bit reference ID. It MUST
        track reference IDs of its servers in order to be able to respond with
        a Reference IDs Response Extension Field.</t>

      <t>For each received request, the server:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Captures a receive timestamp.</t>

          <t>Checks the version in the request. If it is not equal to 5, it
            MUST either drop the request, or handle it according to the
            specification corresponding to the protocol version.</t>

          <t>Drops the request if the format is not valid, mode is not 3, or
            authentication fails with the Message Authentication Code Extension
            Field or another
            authenticator which does not have a specified response for failed
            authentication. The server MUST ignore unknown extension
            fields.</t>

          <t>Server forms a response with requested extension fields and sets
            the fields in the header as follows:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Leap Indicator, Stratum, Root Delay, and Root Dispersion, are
                set to the current server's values.</t>

              <t>Version is set to 5.</t>

              <t>Poll is set to the minimum allowed polling interval of the
                client (e.g. specified in the server configuration, using the
                same value for all clients).</t>

              <t>Precision is set to the expected precision of the receive and
                transmit timestamps included in the response (e.g. estimated on
                the start of the server or specified in its configuration).</t>

              <t>Timescale is set to the client's requested timescale if it is
                supported by the server. If not, the server SHOULD respond in
                any timescale it supports.</t>

              <t>The flags are set as follows:
                <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="Synchronized"> is set if the server's clock is
                    considered to be synchronized, and the receive and transmit
                    timestamps provided in the response are usable for
                    synchronization of the client.</t>
                  <t hangText="Interleaved Mode"> is set if the interleaved
                    mode is implemented, was requested, and a response in the
                    interleaved mode
                    is possible (i.e. a transmit timestamp is associated with
                    the server cookie).</t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>Era is set to the NTP era of the receive timestamp.</t>

              <t>Server Cookie is set when the interleaved
                mode is requested and it is supported by the server, even if
                the response cannot be in the requested mode due to the request
                having an unknown or zero server cookie. The cookie
                identifies a more accurate transmit timestamp of the response,
                which can be retrieved by the client later with another
                request. The cookie MUST be unique in a sufficiently long
                interval to prevent a client from accepting a transmit
                timestamp that does not correspond to the previous response it
                received. The cookie generation is implementation-specific. For
                example, it can be a counter incremented on each received
                request, a randomly generated value, a timestamp, or an
                encrypted counter or timestamp making the value
                unpredictable.</t>

              <t>Client Cookie is set to the Client Cookie from the
                request.</t>

              <t>Receive Timestamp is set to the server's receive timestamp of
                the request.</t>

              <t>Transmit Timestamp is set to a value which depends on the
                measurement mode. In the basic mode it is the server's current
                time when the message is formed. In the interleaved mode it is
                the transmit timestamp of the previous response identified by
                the server cookie in the request, captured at some point after
                the message was formed.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>The length of the response MUST be equal to the length of the
            request. The server adds the Padding Extension Field or increases
            its length if necessary to make the length of the response equal to
            the length of the request.</t>

          <t>Drops the response if it is longer than the request to prevent
            traffic amplification.</t>

          <t>Sends the response.</t>

          <t>Saves the transmit timestamp and server cookie, if the interleaved
            mode was requested and is supported by the server.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="NTPv5 Negotiation in Previous NTP Versions">
      <t>Servers that support multiple versions of NTP MUST send a response in
        the same version as the request, to support backwards compatibility.
        This does not preclude servers from acting as a client in one version
        of NTP and a server in another.</t>

      <t>NTPv5 messages are not compatible with NTPv4 and other previous
        versions of NTP, even if they do not contain any extension fields. Some
        widely used server NTPv4 implementations are known to accept requests
        indicating a higher version, interpreting them as NTPv4, and copying
        the version number from the request to its NTPv4 response. Responses to
        NTPv5 requests have a zero client cookie, which causes them to fail the
        NTPv5 validation and be ignored by the client.</t>

      <t>The implementations are also known to not respond to requests
        with an unknown extension field, which prevents an NTPv4 extension
        field to be specified for NTPv5 negotiation. Instead, the negotiation
        reuses the reference timestamp field.</t>

      <t>An NTP server which supports NTPv5 and also NTPv4, NTPv3, NTPv2, or
        NTPv1, SHOULD check the reference timestamp in received client-mode
        requests of the previous NTP versions. If the reference timestamp
        contains the value 0x4E5450354E545035 ("NTP5NTP5" in ASCII), it
        SHOULD respond with the same reference timestamp to indicate it
        supports NTPv5.</t>

      <t>Note to the editor: Remove this paragraph before publication.
        Implementations of a draft of this specification SHOULD use
        0x4E54503544524654 ("NTP5DRFT" in ASCII) instead of
        0x4E5450354E545035.</t>

      <t>When NTPv5 is not expected to be widely supported on servers yet, an
        NTP client which supports both NTPv5 and a previous NTP version, is not
        configured to use a specific NTP version, and does not use NTS or other
        mechanism including negotiation of the NTP version, SHOULD start with
        the previous version and set the reference timestamp to
        0x4e5450354e545035. If the server responds with the same reference
        timestamp, the client SHOULD switch to NTPv5. If no valid response is
        received for a number of requests (e.g. 2), the client SHOULD switch
        back to the orignal NTP version and stick with it for a larger number
        of requests (e.g. 256) before trying NTPv5 again.</t>

      <t>The special value of the reference timestamp corresponds to
        1941-08-24T01:13:25Z in NTP era 0 and 2077-09-29T07:41:41Z in NTP era
        1. The negotiation will probably not be needed at that time anymore. If
        NTPv5 servers and NTPv4-or-older-only clients are still in use and they
        send a request with the special value by chance, they will get an
        acceptable response with no side effects. If an NTPv5 client gets the
        special value by chance from an NTPv4-or-older-only server, it will
        switch to NTPv5 and back after missing a valid response.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security for NTPv5">
      <t>This document defines two approaches for securing NTPv5 traffic. MAC
        authentication, based on symmetric keys shared between the server and
        client out-of-band. And Network Time Security, which uses existing PKI
        infrastructure to verify the identity of the server on the client.</t>

      <section title="Network Time Security with NTPv5" anchor="network-time-security">
        <t>The <xref target="RFC8915">Network Time Security</xref> mechanism uses
          the NTS-KE protocol to establish keys and negotiate the next protocol.
          NTPv5 can be indicated as the next protocol with identifier [[TBD]] (draft
          use 0x8001). This can be used by clients and servers to negotiate NTPv5
          for an NTS session.</t>

        <t>No new NTS-KE records are specified for NTPv5. The records that were
          specified for NTPv4 (i.e. NTPv4 New Cookie, NTPv4 Server Negotiation,
          and NTPv4 Port Negotiation) are reused for NTPv5.</t>

        <t>The NTS extension fields specified for NTPv4 are compatible with
          NTPv5. No new extension fields are specified.</t>

        <t>(Note to editor: remove this paragraph before publishing.) Client
          implementations of a draft of this specification MUST provide the
          identity of the draft implemented as data in an NTS-KE record of type
          0x4001, which does not have the critical bit set. The draft identity
          MUST be encoded as ascii and MUST not contain any trailing 0 bytes.
          Servers that implement a draft MUST not accept NTPv5 as an option
          unless they support the specific draft version identified.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Message Authentication Code Extension Field"
            anchor="mac-extension-field">
        <t>This field, with type [[TBD]] (draft: 0xF502), authenticates the
          NTPv5 message with a symmetric key known to the client and server.
          Implementations SHOULD use an
          AES-CMAC key to compute the Messace Authentication Code (MAC), as
          recommended in <xref target="RFC8573">RFC8573</xref>. The MAC MUST be
          computed over the NTP header and all the extension fields (including
          padding of fields whose length is not divisble by 4), if present,
          located prior to
          the Message Authentication Code Extension Field.  The extension
          field MUST be the last extension field in the message unless an
          extension field is specifically allowed to be placed after a MAC or
          another authenticator field, such as the
          <xref target="correction-extension-field">Correction Extension
          Field</xref>.</t>

        <t>The format of the Message Authentication Code Extension Field is
          shown in Figure <xref format="counter" target="mac-ext-field"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="mac-ext-field"
            title="Format of Messace Authentication Code Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF502) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                            Key ID                             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                        MAC (variable)                         .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The Key ID is a 32-bit number identifying the key that was used to
          compute the MAC stored in the MAC field. The MAC field MUST contain
          the whole generated MAC. The length depends on the key, e.g. the
          recommended AES-CMAC with an AES-128 key generates 128-bit MACs.</t>

        <t>If a server receives a client request that contains the Message
          Authentication Code Extension Field and the MAC is valid, the
          response, if there is one, MUST include the Message Authentication
          Code Extension Field using the same key as was used in the request.
          If the MAC in the request is not valid, or the key is unknown, the
          server MUST either drop the request, or respond with a message that
          does not contain the Message Authentication Code Extension Field and
          has the Authentication NAK flag set in the header.</t>

        <t>A client configured to use a symmetric key for a given server MUST
          add the Message Authentication Code Extension Field to all requests
          sent to the server. The client MUST accept for synchronization only
          responses that contains a valid MAC using the expected key and the
          MAC is at the expected location in the message (normally the last
          extension field).</t>

        <t>Each client/server pair SHOULD be configured with a different
          symmetric key to prevent other clients and servers from performing
          on-path attacks on the client.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="NTPv5 extensions mandatory for servers">
      <t>In addition to the basic functioning of the protocol described above,
        NTPv5 capable servers SHALL also implement these extensions. Pure
        clients implementations MAY choose to ignore these extensions</t>

      <section title="Server Information Extension Field"
          anchor="server-information-extension-field">
        <t>This field provides clients with information about which NTP
          versions are supported by the server, i.e. whether it can respond to
          requests conforming to the specific version. It contains a 16-bit
          field with flags indicating support for NTP versions in the range of
          1 to 16, where the least significant bit corresponds to the version
          1. The extension field has a fixed length of 8 octets. In requests,
          all data fields of the extension are 0.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="server-information-ext-field"
            title="Format of Server Information Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF505) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Supported NTP versions     |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>This field MUST be supported on servers.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reference IDs Request and Response Extension Fields"
          anchor="reference-ids-extension-fields">
        <t>Each NTPv5 server has a randomly generated 120-bit reference ID
          (it will be split into 10 12-bit values). The
          extension fields described in this section are used to exchange sets
          of reference IDs in order to detect synchronization loops, i.e. when
          a client is synchronizing (directly or indirectly) to one of its own
          clients, or more generally detect presence of a specific time
          source in the synchronization chain.</t>

        <t>As each client can be synchronized to an unlimited number of
          servers (and there can be up to 15 strata of servers), the reference
          IDs are exchanged as a <xref target="Bloom">Bloom filter</xref>
          instead of a list to limit the amount of data that needs to be
          exchanged.</t>

        <t>The Bloom filter is an array of 4096 bits. When empty, all bits are
          zero. To add a reference ID to the filter, the 120-bit value of the
          reference ID is split into 10 12-bit values and the bits of the array
          at the 10 positions given by the 12-bit values are set to one.</t>

        <t>A server maintains a copy of the filter for each server it acquires
          time from. The filter provided by the server to clients is the
          union of the filters (using the bitwise OR operation) of the server's
          sources selected for synchronization and the server's own reference
          ID.</t>

        <t>If the server uses a previous version of NTP for some of its
          sources, the reference IDs added to the filter are generated from
          their IP addresses as the first 120 bits of the
          <xref target="RFC1321">MD5</xref> sum of the address in network
          order. If the server uses a reference clock, the reference ID is the
          first 120 bits of the MD5 sum of the 4-octet zero-padded ASCII
          string from the NTP Reference Identifier Codes registry maintained by
          IANA, or a string beginning with the uppercase letter X, which are
          reserved for private and experimental use.</t>

        <t>A client checking whether the server's set of reference IDs contains
          the client's own reference ID checks whether the bits at the 10
          positions corresponding to the 12-bit values from the reference ID
          are all set to one.</t>

        <t>When a client that also serves time to other clients as an NTPv5
          server detects its reference ID in a server's set of reference IDs,
          it SHOULD assume it is in a synchronization loop, and stop using
          that server for synchronization. When the client's reference ID is
          no longer detected in the server's filter, it SHOULD wait for a
          random number of polling intervals (e.g. between 0 and 4) before
          selecting the server again. The random delay helps with stabilization
          of the selection in longer loops. If a recurring loop is detected,
          it is recommended to increase the random delay in order to avoid
          livelock scenarios.</t>

        <t>False positives are possible. The probability of a collision grows
          with the number of reference IDs in the filter. With 26 reference IDs
          it is about 1e-12. With 118 IDs it is about 1e-6. The client MAY avoid
          selecting a server which has too many bits set in the filter (e.g.
          more than half) to reduce the probability of the collision for its
          own clients. A client which detected a synchronization loop MAY
          change its own reference ID to limit the duration of the potential
          collision.</t>

        <t>Bloom filters are free from false negatives. However, there is a
          transient period between the addition of a reference ID to a server's
          Bloom filter and the propagation of this information through a chain
          of clients. During this period, the new reference ID may not be
          detected, potentially causing a temporary synchronization loop. For
          instance, if two servers inquire each other about the list of
          reference IDs roughly at the same time, neither will detect its
          reference ID in the other's Bloom filter, resulting in a temporary
          loop.</t>

        <t>Generally, when a server updates the Bloom filter it distributes to
          clients, temporary synchronization loops might occur before
          converging to an acyclic distribution tree.</t>

        <t>The filter can be exchanged as a single 512-octet array, or it can
          be exchanged in smaller chunks over multiple NTP messages, making
          them shorter, but delaying the detection of the synchronization
          loop.</t>

        <t>The request extension field specifies the offset of the requested
          chunk in the filter as a number of octets. The requested length of
          the chunk is given by the length of data in the request extension
          field. The response extension field MUST have the same length as the
          request extension field. If the request contains an invalid offset
          for the length, i.e. it is larger than 512 minus length of data in
          the extension field, the extension field MUST be ignored.</t>

        <t>When a filter is sent to a client in multiple chunks, the server
          might update the Bloom filter to a new value after some chunks have
          been sent. This can cause the subsequent chunks to be inconsistent
          with the previously sent ones. The partially updated Bloom filter
          might cause false negative or false positive detections. This
          transient issue is resolved once the server completes sending the
          updated Bloom filter.</t>

        <t>The client SHOULD use requests of a constant length for the
          association to avoid adding a variation to the measured NTP
          delay.</t>

        <t>The format of the Reference IDs Request is shown in Figure <xref
          format="counter" target="reference-ids-req-ext-field"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="reference-ids-req-ext-field"
            title="Format of Reference IDs Request Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF503) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Offset             |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
.                                                               .
.                        Padding (variable)                     .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The format of the Reference IDs Response is shown in Figure <xref
          format="counter" target="reference-ids-res-ext-field"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="reference-ids-res-ext-field"
            title="Format of Reference IDs Response Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF504) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                  Bloom filter chunk (variable)                .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>These fields MUST be supported on servers which can be synchronized
          to other NTP servers (i.e. they can be in a synchronization loop).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Optional extensions to NTPv5">
      <t>The following features are optional for both clients and servers.
        Implementations MAY choose to ignore these features.</t>

      <section title="Interleaved mode" anchor="interleaved-mode">
        <t>The NTPv4 interleaved client-server mode is described in <xref
          target="RFC9769">RFC 9769</xref>. The difference between NTPv5 and
          NTPv4 is that in NTPv5 the interleaved mode is enabled explicitly by a
          flag and the previous transmit timestamp on the server is identified by
          the server cookie instead of the receive timestamp, which avoids the
          requirements for receive timestamps to be unique and not equal to
          transmit timestamps. Therefore, the NTPv5 interleaved mode is easier to
          implement. A server implementation that supports both NTPv4 and
          NTPv5 does not need to process interleaved requests and save timestamps
          separately for the different NTP versions. It can reuse the NTPv4
          support in NTPv5 by setting the server cookie to the (unique) receive
          timestamp.</t>

        <t>An example of an NTPv5 exchange using the interleaved mode is shown in
          Figure <xref format="counter" target="interleaved-exchange"></xref>.
          The messages in the basic and interleaved mode are indicated with B and
          I respectively. The timestamps t3' and t11' correspond to the same
          transmissions as t3 and t11, but they may be less accurate (e.g. due to
          being captured in software before the transmission). The first
          exchange is in the basic mode followed by a second exchange in the
          interleaved mode. For the third exchange, the client request is in the
          interleaved mode, but the server response is in the basic mode, because
          the server no longer had the timestamp t7 (e.g. it was dropped to save
          timestamps for other clients using the interleaved mode).</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="interleaved-exchange"
            title="Cookies and timestamps in interleaved mode">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
  Server   t2   t3               t6   t7              t10  t11
      -----+----+----------------+----+----------------+----+-----
          /      \              /      \              /      \
  Client /        \            /        \            /        \
      --+----------+----------+----------+----------+----------+--
        t1         t4         t5         t8         t9        t12

  Mode: B         B           I         I           I         B
      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+
  SC  | 0  |    | s1 |      | s1 |    | s2 |      | s2 |    | s3 |
  CC  | c1 |    | c1 |      | c2 |    | c2 |      | c3 |    | c3 |
  Rx  | 0  |    | t2 |      | 0  |    | t6 |      | 0  |    |t10 |
  Tx  | 0  |    | t3'|      | 0  |    | t3 |      | 0  |    |t11'|
      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>From the three exchanges in this example, the client would use the
          following sets of timestamps:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>(t1, t2, t3', t4)</t>
            <t>(t1, t2, t3, t4) or (t5, t6, t3, t4)</t>
            <t>(t9, t10, t11', t12)</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Correction Extension Field" anchor="correction-extension-field">

        <t>Processing and queueing delays in network switches and routers may
          be a significant source of jitter and asymmetry in network delay,
          which has a negative impact on accuracy and stability of clocks
          synchronized by NTP. A solution to this problem is defined in the
          <xref target="IEEE1588">Precision Time Protocol (PTP)</xref>, which
          is a different protocol for synchronization of clocks in networks. In
          PTP a special type of switch or router, called a Transparent Clock
          (TC), updates a correction field in PTP messages to account for the
          time messages spend in the TC. This is accomplished by timestamping
          the message at the ingress and egress ports, taking the difference to
          determine time in the TC and adding this to the Delay Correction.
          Clients can account for the accumulated Delay Correction to determine
          a more accurate clock offset and network delay.</t>

        <t>The NTPv5 Delay Correction has the same format as the PTP
          correctionField to make it easier for manufacturers of switches and
          routers to implement NTP corrections. The format of the Correction
          Extension Field is shown in Figure <xref format="counter"
          target="correction-ext-field"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="correction-ext-field"
                title="Format of Correction Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF506) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                       Origin Correction                       +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        Origin Path ID         |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                       Delay Correction                        +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Delay Path ID           |     Checksum Complement       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Field Type"><vspace/>
               The type which identifies the Correction extension field (value
               TBD).</t>

            <t hangText="Length"><vspace/>
               The length of the extension field, which is 28 octets.</t>

            <t hangText="Origin Correction"><vspace/>
               A field which contains a copy of the accumulated delay
               correction from the request packet in the NTP exchange.</t>

            <t hangText="Origin Path ID"><vspace/>
               A field which contains a copy of the final path ID from the
               request packet in the NTP exchange.</t>

            <t hangText="Reserved"><vspace/>
               16 bit reserved for future specification by the IETF.
               Transmit with all zeros.</t>

            <t hangText="Delay Correction"><vspace/>
               A signed fixed-point number of nanoseconds with 48 integer
               bits and 16 binary fractional bits, which represents the current
               correction of the network delay that has accumulated for this
               packet on the path from the source to the destination. A value
               of one in all bits, except the most significant, of the field
               indicates that the correction is too big to be represented.
               The format of this field is identical to the PTP
               correctionField.</t>

            <t hangText="Path ID"><vspace/>
               A 16-bit identification number of the path where the delay
               correction was updated.</t>

            <t hangText="Checksum Complement"><vspace/>
               A field which can be modified in order to keep the UDP
               checksum of the packet valid. This allows the UDP checksum
               to be transmitted before the Correction Field is received and
               modified. The same field is described in <xref
               target="RFC7821">RFC 7821</xref>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>An NTP client with enabled support for network corrections SHOULD
          add the Correction Extension Field to its requests, with all fields
          of the extension field set to zero. It MUST be the last extension
          field in the NTP message.</t>

        <t>A network device forwarding packets (e.g. a switch or router) with
          enabled support for NTP corrections MUST modify only packets which
          meet all of the following requirements:

          <list style="numbers">
            <t>It is an IPv4 or IPv6 packet</t>
            <t>The IP protocol number is 17 (UDP)</t>
            <t>The UDP source port or destination port is 123 (NTP)</t>
            <t>The NTP version is 5</t>
            <t>The NTP message contains the Correction Extension Field</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>The network device SHOULD add the difference between the beginning of
          the NTP message retransmission and the end of the message reception to
          the Delay Correction value in the Correction Extension Field. Note
          that this time difference might be negative, e.g. in a cut-through
          switch. If the packet is transmitted at the same speed as it was
          received and the length of the packet does not change (e.g. due to
          adding or removing a VLAN tag), the beginning and end of the interval
          may correspond to any point of the reception and transmission as long
          as it is consistent for all forwarded packets of the same length. If
          the transmission speed or length of the packet is different, the
          beginning and end of the interval SHOULD correspond to the end of the
          reception and beginning of the transmission respectively.</t>

        <t>The receive timestamp of the ingress port and transmit timestamp of
          the egress port MUST be from the same clock, or two clocks that are
          synchronized to each other. The clocks do not need to be synchronized
          to an external reference if their frequency is accurate enough for
          the accuracy of measured NTP delay required by the application. The
          correction field is updated before or during the transmission of the
          message. It is a one-step end-to-end transparent clock in the PTP
          terminology.</t>

        <t>The network device SHOULD have a randomly generated 16-bit ID
          number assigned to each of its ports. When it modifies the Correction
          Extension Field, it SHOULD update the Path ID field of the extension
          field by adding to it the values of the incoming and outgoing port
          ID. The Path ID values can be used by clients to determine if the NTP
          request and response have likely traversed the same network path.</t>

        <t>If the network device modified any fields of the Correction
          Extension Field, it MUST also update the Checksum Complement field in
          order to keep the existing UDP checksum valid, or update the UDP
          checksum in the UDP header itself. The network device MUST NOT modify
          any other data in the UDP payload.</t>

        <t>If an NTP server supports the Correction Extension Field and
          receives a request which contains this extension field, it SHOULD
          include the extension field in the response. If it is included, it
          MUST be the last extension field in the message. It MUST copy the
          Delay Correction and Path ID from the request to the Origin
          Correction and Origin Path ID fields in the response respectively. It
          SHOULD set the Delay Correction and Path ID fields of the response to
          zero.</t>

        <t>The Correction Extension Field is required to be the last extension
          field in the message to provide an indicator at a fixed offset from
          the ending of the message reception (which might simplify hardware
          implementation of the correction) and to avoid being covered by the
          Message Authentication Code Extension Field, or other
          authenticator extension fields (e.g. Network Time Security). It is
          the exception in the requirement specified for the Message
          Authentication Code Extension Field. If the corrections were
          covered by the authenticator fields, the network devices would need
          to have access to the keys and have a significant additional
          complexity in order to update the authenticator fields when they
          modify the Correction Extension Field.</t>

        <t>As the Correction Extension Field is not protected, NTP clients
          MUST validate the corrections before their application as specified
          in <xref target="measurement-modes">Measurement Modes</xref>. Clients
          MUST ignore an unexpected Correction Extension Field in the response,
          i.e. if it was not included in the request.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reference Timestamp Extension Field"
          anchor="reference-timestamp-extension-field">
        <t>This field contains the time of the last update of the clock. It
          has a fixed length of 12 octets. In requests, that timestamp is always
          0.</t>

        <t>(Is this really needed? It was mostly unused in NTPv4.)</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="reference-timestamp-ext-field"
            title="Format of Reference Timestamp Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF507) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                      Reference Timestamp (64)                 |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Monotonic Receive Timestamp Extension Field"
          anchor="monotonic-receive-timestamp-extension-field">

        <t>When a clock is synchronized to a time source, there is a compromise
          between time (phase) accuracy and frequency accuracy, because the
          frequency of the clock has to be adjusted to correct time errors that
          accumulate due to the frequency error (e.g. caused by changes in the
          temperature of the crystal). Faster corrections of time can minimize
          the time error, but increase the frequency error, which transfers to
          clients using that clock as a time source and increases their
          frequency and time errors. This issue can be avoided by transferring
          time and frequency separately using different clocks.</t>

        <t>The Monotonic Receive Timestamp Extension Field contains an extra
          receive timestamp with a 32-bit epoch ID captured by a clock which
          does not have corrected phase and can better transfer frequency than
          the clock which captures the receive and transmit timestamps in the
          header. The extension field has a constant length of 16 octets. In
          requests, the counter and timestamp are always 0.</t>

        <t>The epoch ID is a random number which is changed when
          frequency transfer needs to be restarted, e.g. due to a step of the
          clock.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="monotonic-timestamp-ext-field"
            title="Format of Monotonic Receive Timestamp Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF508) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                            Epoch ID                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                  Monotonic Receive Timestamp (64)             |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The client can determine the frequency-transfer offset from the
          time-transfer offset and difference between the two receive
          timestamps in the response. It can use the frequency-transfer offset
          to better control the frequency of its clock, avoiding the frequency
          error in the server's time-transfer clock.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Secondary Receive Timestamp Extension Field"
          anchor="secondary-receive-timestamp-extension-field">
        <t>This extension field provides an additional receive timestamp of the
          client request in a selected timescale. It enables the client to get
          the same receive timestamp in different timescales in order to
          calculate the current offset between the timescales.</t>

        <t>In requests, the Timescale field selects the requested timescale.
          The other data fields in the extension field MUST be set to 0.</t>

        <t>The Timescale, Era, and Secondary Receive Timestamp fields in a
          response have the same meaning as the Timescale, Era, and Receive
          Timestamp fields in the header respectively.</t>

        <t>If the server does not support the requested timescale, it MUST
          ignore the extension field in the request. If the server supports the
          timescale, but does not have a reliable timestamp (e.g. due to being
          close to a leap second), it SHOULD set the timestamp field to 0.</t>

        <t>The server MAY provide in this extension field timestamps in
          timescales which it does not provide in the header, e.g. it can
          provide UTC in addition to leap-smeared UTC to enable its clients to
          measure the current smearing offset.</t>

        <t>A request MAY contain multiple instances of this extension field,
          but each timescale MUST be requested at most once, not counting the
          timescale in the header. The server SHOULD include in its response
          timestamps in all requested timescales it supports.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="secondary-receive-timestamp-ext-field"
            title="Format of Secondary Receive Timestamp Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF509) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Timescale   |      Era      |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                Secondary Receive Timestamp (64)               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to allocate the following entries in the <xref
        target="RFC9748">NTP Extension Field Types Registry</xref>:</t>

      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Field Type</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Meaning</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Padding</c>
        <c><xref target="padding-extension-field">[[this memo]]</xref></c>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Message Authentication Code</c>
        <c><xref target="mac-extension-field">[[this memo]]</xref></c>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Reference IDs Request</c>
        <c><xref target="reference-ids-extension-fields">[[this memo]]</xref></c>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Reference IDs Response</c>
        <c><xref target="reference-ids-extension-fields">[[this memo]]</xref></c>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Server Information</c>
        <c><xref target="server-information-extension-field">
          [[this memo]]</xref></c>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Correction</c>
        <c><xref target="correction-extension-field">[[this memo]]</xref></c>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Reference Timestamp</c>
        <c><xref target="reference-timestamp-extension-field">
          [[this memo]]</xref></c>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Monotonic Receive Timestamp</c>
        <c><xref target="monotonic-receive-timestamp-extension-field">
          [[this memo]]</xref></c>

        <c>[[TBD]]</c>
        <c>Secondary Receive Timestamp</c>
        <c><xref target="secondary-receive-timestamp-extension-field">
          [[this memo]]</xref></c>
      </texttable>

      <t>IANA is requested to allocate the following entry in the
        <xref target="RFC8915">Network Time Security Next Protocols
          Registry</xref>:</t>

      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Protocol ID</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Protocol Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Network Time Protocol version 5 (NTPv5)</c>
        <c><xref target="network-time-security">[[this memo]]</xref></c>
      </texttable>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations of time protocols in general are discussed
        in <xref target="RFC7384"/>. A successful attack on the time
        distribution can result in one of three outcomes: Denial of Service
        (DoS), reduced accuracy, or obtaining incorrect time. NTP can be
        compromised through various methods, such as altering or delaying NTP
        messages during transit, injecting malicious NTP messages or replaying
        valid ones, or impersonating an NTP server.</t>

      <t>The Message Authentication Code (MAC) Extension Field can be used to
        provide integrity protection, thus mitigating in-transit NTP message
        modification and malicious packet injection.</t>

      <t>Using NTS with NTPv5 provides enhanced security properties, including
        server identity verification, improved replay protection, and secure
        key establishment.</t>

      <t>Downgrading attacks that could lead to an adversary disabling or
        removing encryption or authentication are not possible in NTPv5, since
        the use of the security mechanism, either MAC or NTS, is determined by
        configuration, and not by negotiation.</t>

      <t>NTPv5 was designed to minimize the necessary on-the-wire data that is
        included in the NTPv5 header in order to limit the amount of
        information that is exposed to the network and minimize the potential
        effect of network reconnaissance. For example, the client's
        transmission timestamp is not included in the NTPv5 header. Extension
        fields are used for conveying optional information.</t>

      <t>The protocol operates in a client-server mode. Other modes of
        operation, which were supported in the previous version of the protocol
        have known security vulnerabilities. The symmetric and broadcast modes
        are vulnerable to replay attacks. The control and private modes can be
        exploited for denial-of-service traffic amplification attacks. These
        modes are not supported in NTPv5.</t>

      <t>The NTP response message has the same length as the corresponding
        request message. This symmetric approach reduces the potential of
        amplification attacks.</t>

      <t>The protocol does not inherently mitigate delay attacks. An on-path
        attacker can delay NTP messages and compromise the accuracy. Delay
        attacks can be mitigated by limiting the maximum acceptable delay. In
        each request-response exchange the client computes the delay and can
        discard the response if the delay exceeds a maximum expected value. A
        more fine-grained mitigation approach is acquiring time from multiple
        sources and selecting the sources that are most likely to be accurate.
        A detailed scheme was defined in <xref target="RFC5905"/> and can be
        used in NTPv5. This scheme defines a selection algorithm, which
        identifies the most accurate and reliable time sources from a pool of
        candidates. These sources are then grouped by the clustering algorithm
        to minimize the impact of outliers. Finally, the combining algorithm
        averages the time data from these clustered sources to produce a final,
        stable time estimate. An enhancement to the selection algorithm was
        proposed in <xref target="RFC9523"/>. An alternative approach to using
        multiple time sources is using multiple diverse paths between the
        client and server <xref target="RFC8039"/>, as it is assumed that only
        a subset of the paths is compromised by an on-path attacker.</t>

      <t>The corrections provided by network devices in the Correction
        Extension Field are not authenticated. On-path attackers can
        modify the correction values. In order to mitigate such attacks, the
        client validates the correction values as described in <xref
        target="measurement-modes"/>. Thus, only corrections smaller than the
        measured delay are accepted by clients. The security impact is
        comparable to the impact of delaying unmodified NTP messages, as
        described above.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Some ideas were taken from a different NTPv5 design proposed by Daniel
        Franke.</t>

      <t>The author would like to thank Doug Arnold and David Venhoek for their
        contributions and Dan Drown, Richard Laager, Watson Ladd, Hal Murray,
        Kurt Roeckx, Dieter Sibold, Brett Vickers, and Ulrich Windl for their
        suggestions and comments.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC1321;

      &RFC2119;

      &RFC8174;

      &RFC8573;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC5905;

      &RFC7384;

      &RFC7821;

      &RFC7822;

      &RFC8039;

      &RFC8877;

      &RFC8915;

      &RFC9523;

      &RFC9748;

      &RFC9769;

      <reference anchor="IEEE1588" target="https://www.ieee.org">
        <front>
          <title>
            IEEE std. 1588-2019, "IEEE Standard for a Precision Clock
            Synchronization for Networked Measurement and Control
            Systems."
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>
              Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="11" year="2019" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Bloom" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/362686.362692">
        <front>
          <title>Space/Time Trade-Offs in Hash Coding with Allowable Errors</title>
          <author surname="Bloom" fullname="Burton H. Bloom">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="6" year="1970" />
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
