<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1321 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1321.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5905 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7384 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7384.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7821 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7821.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8573 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8573.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8915 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8915.xml">
<!ENTITY XLEAVE SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ntp-interleaved-modes.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-mlichvar-ntp-ntpv5-06" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>Network Time Protocol Version 5</title>

    <author fullname="Miroslav Lichvar" initials="M." surname="Lichvar">
      <organization>Red Hat</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Purkynova 115</street>
          <city>Brno</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>612 00</code>
          <country>Czech Republic</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mlichvar@redhat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2022" month="Dec" day="6"/>

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>NTP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the version 5 of the Network Time Protocol (NTP).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Network Time Protocol (NTP) is a protocol which enables computers to
        synchronize their clocks over network. Time is distributed from primary
        time servers to clients, which can be servers for other clients, and so
        on. Clients can use multiple servers simultaneously.</t>

      <t>NTPv5 is similar to <xref target="RFC5905">NTPv4</xref>. The main
        differences are:

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The protocol specification (this document) describes only the
            on-wire protocol. Filtering of measurements, security mechanisms,
            source selection, clock control, and other algorithms, are out of
            scope.</t>

          <t>For security reasons, NTPv5 drops support for the symmetric
            active, symmetric passive, broadcast, control, and private modes.
            The symmetric and broadcast modes are vulnerable to replay attacks.
            The control and private modes can be exploited for
            denial-of-service traffic amplification attacks. Only the client
            and server modes remain in NTPv5.</t>

          <t>Timestamps are clearly separated from values used as cookies.</t>

          <t>NTPv5 messages can be extended only with extension fields. The MAC
            field is wrapped in an extension field.</t>

          <t>Extension fields can be of any length, even indivisible by 4, but are
            padded to a multiple of 4 octets. Extension fields specified for
            NTPv4 are compatible with NTPv5.</t>

          <t>NTPv5 adds support for other timescales than UTC.</t>

          <t>The NTP era number is exchanged in the protocol, which extends the
            unambiguous interval of the client from 136 years to about 35000
            years.</t>

          <t>NTPv5 adds interleaved mode to provide clients with more
            accurate transmit timestamps.</t>

          <t>NTPv5 works with sets of reference IDs to prevent synchronization
            loops over multiple hosts.</t>

          <t>Resolution of the root delay and root dispersion fields is
            improved from about 15 microseconds to about 4 nanoseconds.</t>

          <t>Clients don't leak information about their clock (e.g.
            timestamps).</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
          "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
          capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Basic Concepts">
      <t>The distance to the reference time sources in the hierarchy of servers
        is called stratum. Primary time servers, which are synchronized to the
        reference clocks, are stratum 1, their clients are stratum 2, and so
        on.</t>

      <t>Root delay measures the total delay on the path to the reference time
        source used by the primary time server. Each client on the path adds to
        the root delay the NTP delay measured to the server it considers best
        for synchronization. The delay includes network delays and any delays
        between timestamping of NTP messages and their actual reception and
        transmission. Half of the root delay estimates the maximum error of the
        clock due to asymmetries in the delay.</t>

      <t>Root dispersion estimates the maximum error of the clock due to the
        instability of the clocks on the path and instability of NTP
        measurements. Each server on the path adds its own dispersion to the
        root dispersion. Different clock models can be used. In a simple model,
        the clock can have a constant dispersion rate, e.g. 15 ppm as used in
        NTPv4.</t>

      <t>The sum of the root dispersion and half of the root delay is called
        root distance. It is the estimated maximum error of the clock, taking
        into account asymmetry in delay and stability of clocks and
        measurements.</t>

      <t>Servers have randomly generated reference IDs to enable detection and
        prevention of synchronization loops.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Data Types">
      <t>NTPv5 uses few different data types. They are all in the network
        order. Beside signed and unsigned integers, it has also the following
        fixed-point types:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="time16"><vspace/>
            A 16-bit signed fixed-point type containing values in seconds. It has 1
            signed integer bit (i.e. it is just the sign) and 15 fractional
            bits. The minimum value is the fraction -32767/32768 (almost -1
            second), the maximum value is 32767/32768 (almost 1 second), and
            the resolution is about 30 microseconds. The type has a special
            value of 0x8000, which indicates an unknown value or value that is
            too large to be represented by this type.</t>

          <t hangText="time32"><vspace/>
            A 32-bit unsigned fixed-point type containing values in seconds. It
            has 4 bits describing the unsigned integral part and 28 bits
            describing the fractional part. The maximum value is
            16 seconds and the resolution is about 3.7 nanoseconds. Note that
            this is different from the 32-bit time format in NTPv4.</t>

          <t hangText="time64"><vspace/>
            A 64 bit signed fixed-point type containg values in seconds. It has 32
            signed integer bits, and 32 fractional bits. The sign uses 2-complements
            representation for negative numbers.
          </t>

          <t hangText="timestamp64"><vspace/>
            A 64-bit unsigned fixed-point type containing a timestamp describes
            in seconds. It has 32 signed
            integer bits and 32 fractional bits. It spans an interval of about
            136 years and has a resolution of about 0.23 nanoseconds. It can be
            used in different timescales. In the UTC timescale it is the number
            of SI seconds since 1 Jan 1972 plus 2272060800 (number of seconds
            since 1 Jan 1900 assuming 86400-second days), excluding leap
            seconds. Timestamps in the TAI timescale are the same except they
            include leap seconds and extra 10 seconds for the original
            difference between TAI and UTC in 1972, when leap seconds were
            introduced. One interval covered by the type is called an NTP era.
            The era starting at the epoch is era number 0, the following era is
            number 1, and so on.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Some fields use a logarithmic scale, where an 8-bit signed integer
        represents the rounded log2 value of seconds. For example, a log2 value
        of 4 is 2^4 (2 to the power of 4, 16) seconds, or a log2 value of -2
        is 2^-2 (0.25 seconds).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Message Format">
      <t>NTPv5 servers and clients exchange messages as UDP datagrams. Clients
        send requests to servers and servers send them back responses. The
        format of the UDP payload is shown in Figure <xref format="counter"
          target="message-format"/>.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="message-format"
          title="Format of NTPv5 messages">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|LI | VN  |Mode |    Stratum    |     Poll      |  Precision    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Timescale   |      Era      |             Flags             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           Root Delay                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Root Dispersion                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                        Server Cookie (64)                     +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                        Client Cookie (64)                     +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                      Receive Timestamp (64)                   +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                      Transmit Timestamp (64)                  +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                    Extension Field 1 (variable)               .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                                                               .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                    Extension Field N (variable)               .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Each NTPv5 message has a header containing the following fields:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Leap indicator (LI)"><vspace/>
            A 2-bit field which can have the following values: 0 (normal), 1
            (leap second inserted at the end of the month), 2 (leap second
            deleted at the end of the month), 3 (not synchronized). The values
            1 and 2 are set at most 14 days in advance before the leap second.
            In requests it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Version Number (VN)"><vspace/>
            A 3-bit field containing the value 5.</t>

          <t hangText="Mode"><vspace/>
            A 3-bit field containing the value 3 (request) or 4 (response).</t>

          <t hangText="Stratum"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit field containing the stratum of the server. Primary time
            servers have a stratum of 1, their clients have a stratum of 2, and
            so on. The value of 0 indicates an unknown or infinite stratum. In
            requests it is always 0. Servers advertising a stratum above 16
            should not be synchronized to except when the client is explicitly
            configured to do so by the end-user.</t>

          <t hangText="Poll"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit signed integer containing the polling interval as a
            rounded log2 value in seconds. In requests it is the current
            polling interval. In responses it is the minimum allowed polling
            interval.</t>

          <t hangText="Precision"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit signed integer containing the precision of the timestamps
            included in the message as a rounded log2 value in seconds. In
            requests, which don't contain any timestamps, it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Timescale"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit identifier of the timescale. In requests it is the
            requested timescale. In responses it is the timescale of the
            receive and transmit timestamps. Defined values are:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t>0: UTC</t>
              <t>1: TAI</t>
              <t>2: UT1</t>
              <t>3: Leap-smeared UTC</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t hangText="Era"><vspace/>
            An 8-bit unsigned NTP era number corresponding to the receive
            timestamp. In requests it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Flags"><vspace/>
            A 16-bit integer that can contain the following flags:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="0x1: Unknown leap"><vspace/>
                In requests it is 0. In responses a value of 1 indicates the
                server does not have a time source which provides information
                about leap seconds and the client should interpret the Leap
                Indicator as having only two possible values: synchronized (0)
                and not synchronized (3).</t>
              <t hangText="0x2: Interleaved mode"><vspace/>
                In requests a value of 1 is a request for a response in the
                interleaved mode. In responses a value of 1 indicates the
                response is in the interleaved mode.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t hangText="Root Delay"><vspace/>
            A field using the time32 type. In responses it is the server's root
            delay. In requests it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Root Dispersion"><vspace/>
            A field using the time32 type. In responses it is the server's root
            dispersion. In requests it is always 0.</t>

          <t hangText="Server Cookie"><vspace/>
            A 64-bit field containing a number generated by the server which
            enables the interleaved mode. In requests it is 0, or a copy of the
            server cookie from the last response.</t>

          <t hangText="Client Cookie"><vspace/>
            A 64-bit field containing a random number generated by the client.
            Responses contain a copy of the field from the corresponding
            request, which allows the client to verify that the responses
            are related to the requests.</t>

          <t hangText="Receive Timestamp"><vspace/>
            A field using the timestamp64 type. In requests it is always
            0. In responses it is the time when the request was received by
            the server. The
            timestamp corresponds to the end of the reception.</t>

          <t hangText="Transmit Timestamp"><vspace/>
            A field using the timestamp64 type. In requests it is always
            0. In responses it is the server's time denoting the beginning of
            the transmission of a
            response to the client. Which response it refers to depends
            on the selected mode (basic or interleaved). See <xref
            target="measurement-modes">Measurement Modes</xref> for detail.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The header has 48 octets, which is the minimum length of a valid NTPv5
        message. A message can contain optional extension fields (zero or more).
        The maximum length is not specified, but the length MUST be divisible
        by 4.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Extension Fields">
      <t>The format of NTPv5 extension fields is shown in Figure <xref
          format="counter" target="extension-field"/>.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="extension-field"
          title="Format of NTPv5 extension fields">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|             Type              |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                           Data (variable)                     .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Each extension field has a header which contains a 16-bit type and
        16-bit length. The length is in octets and it includes the header. The
        minimum length is 4, i.e. an extension field does not have to contain
        any data. If the length is not divisible by 4, the extension field is
        padded with zeros to the smallest multiple of 4 octets.</t>

      <t>If a request contains an extension field, the server MUST include this
        extension field in the response unless the specification of the
        extension field states otherwise, or the server does not support the
        extension field. A client can interpret the absence of an expected
        extension field in a response as an indication that the server does not
        support the extension field.</t>

      <t>Extension fields specified for NTPv4 can be included in NTPv5 messages
        as specified for NTPv4.</t>

      <t>The rest of this section describes extension fields specified for
        NTPv5. Clients are not required to use or support any of these
        extension fields, but servers are required to support at least the
        Padding Extension Field, and if they can be synchronized to another
        server, also the Reference IDs Request and Response extension fields to
        enable detection of synchronization loops.</t>

      <section title="Draft Identification Extension Field">
        <t>Note to the editors: this section must be removed before final publication.</t>

        <t>This field, with type 0xF5FF, is used to indicate which draft of the specification
          an implementation is based upon. It MUST be included in NTPv5 requests produced
          by an implementation based on a draft of this specification, and MUST NOT be included
          in NTPv5 requests produced by an implementation based on the final version of
          this specification. Server MUST use this field if and only if responding
          to a request containing this field and the server is a draft
          implementation.</t>

        <t>The contents of this field MUST be the full name, including version number, of
          the draft upon which the implementation is based, encoded as an ASCII
          string. If the server string is longer than the client string, the
          server MUST truncate it to the length of the client string.</t>

        <t>Note: the content of this field MUST NOT be null terminated</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Padding Extension Field">
        <t>This field, with type [[TBD]] (draft: 0xF501), is used by servers to pad the response to the same length
          as the request if the response does not contain all requested
          extension fields, or some have a variable length. It can have any
          length. The data field of the extension field SHOULD contain zeros
          and it MUST be ignored by the receiver.</t>

        <t>This field MUST be supported on servers.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MAC Extension Field">
        <t>This field, with type [[TBD]] (draft: 0xF502), authenticates the NTPv5 message with a symmetric key.
          Implementations SHOULD use the MAC specified in <xref
          target="RFC8573">RFC8573</xref>. The extension field MUST be the last
          extension field in the message unless an extension field is
          specifically allowed to be placed after a MAC or another
          authenticator field.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reference IDs Request and Response Extension Fields">
        <t>Each NTPv5 server has a randomly generated 120-bit reference ID
          (it will be split into 10 12-bit values). The
          extension fields described in this section are used to exchange sets
          of reference IDs in order to detect synchronization loops, i.e. when
          a client is synchronizing (directly or indirectly) to one of its own
          clients.</t>

        <t>As each client can be synchronized to an unlimited number of
          servers (and there can be up to 15 strata of servers), the reference
          IDs are exchanged as a <xref target="Bloom">Bloom filter</xref>
          instead of a list to limit the amount of data that needs to be
          exchanged.</t>

        <t>The Bloom filter is an array of 4096 bits. When empty, all bits are
          zero. To add a reference ID to the filter, the 120-bit value of the
          reference ID is split into 10 12-bit values and the bits of the array
          at the 10 positions given by the 12-bit values are set to one.</t>

        <t>A server maintains a copy of the filter for each server it is using
          as an NTP client. The filter provided by the server to clients is the
          union of the filters (using the bitwise OR operation) of the server's
          sources selected for synchronization and the server's own reference
          ID.</t>

        <t>If the server uses a previous version of NTP for some of its
          sources, the reference IDs added to the filter are generated from
          their IP addresses as the first 120 bits of the
          <xref target="RFC1321">MD5</xref> sum of the address.</t>

        <t>A client checking whether the server's set of reference IDs contains
          the client's own reference ID checks whether the bits at the 10
          positions corresponding to the 12-bit values from the reference ID
          are all set to one.</t>

        <t>When a client which serves time to other clients detects a
          synchronization loop with one of its servers, it SHOULD stop using
          the server for synchronization. When the client's reference ID is
          no longer detected in the server's filter, it SHOULD wait for a
          random number of polling intervals (e.g. between 0 and 4) before
          selecting the server again. The random delay helps with stabilization
          of the selection in longer loops.</t>

        <t>False positives are possible. The probability of a collision grows
          with the number of reference IDs in the filter. With 26 reference IDs
          it is about 1e-12. With 118 IDs it is about 1e-6. The client MAY avoid
          selecting a server which has too many bits set in the filter (e.g.
          more than half) to reduce the probability of the collision for its
          own clients. A client which detected a synchronization loop MAY
          change its own reference ID to limit the duration of the potential
          collision.</t>

        <t>The filter can be exchanged as a single 512-octet array, or it can
          be exchanged in smaller chunks over multiple NTP messages, making
          them shorter, but delaying the detection of the synchronization
          loop.</t>

        <t>The request extension field specifies the offset of the requested
          chunk in the filter as a number of octets. The requested length of
          the chunk is given by the length of the extension field. The response
          extension field MUST have the same length as the request extension
          field. If the request contains an invalid offset, the extension field
          MUST be ignored.</t>

        <t>The client SHOULD use requests of a constant length for the
          association to avoid adding a variation to the measured NTP
          delay.</t>

        <t>The format of the Reference IDs Request is shown in Figure <xref
          format="counter" target="reference-ids-req-ext-field"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="reference-ids-req-ext-field"
            title="Format of Reference IDs Request Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF503) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Offset             |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
.                                                               .
.                        Padding (variable)                     .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The format of the Reference IDs Response is shown in Figure <xref
          format="counter" target="reference-ids-res-ext-field"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="reference-ids-res-ext-field"
            title="Format of Reference IDs Response Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF504) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                  Bloom filter chunk (variable)                .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>These fields MUST be supported on servers which can be synchronized
          to other NTP servers (i.e. they can be in a synchronization loop).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Server Information Extension Field">
        <t>This field provides clients with information about which NTP
          versions are supported by the server, i.e. whether it can respond to
          requests conforming to the specific version. It contains a 16-bit
          field with flags indicating support for NTP versions in the range of
          1 to 16, where the least significant bit corresponds to the version
          1. The extension field has a fixed length of 8 octets. In requests,
          all data fields of the extension are 0.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="server-information-ext-field"
            title="Format of Server Information Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF505) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Supported NTP versions     |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>This field MUST be supported on servers.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Correction Extension Field">

        <t>Processing and queueing delays in network switches and routers may
          be a significant source of jitter and asymmetry in network delay,
          which has a negative impact on accuracy and stability of clocks
          synchronized by NTP. A solution to this problem is defined in the
          <xref target="IEEE1588">Precision Time Protocol (PTP)</xref>, which
          is a different protocol for synchronization of clocks in networks. In
          PTP a special type of switch or router, called a Transparent Clock
          (TC), updates a correction field in PTP messages to account for the
          time messages spend in the TC. This is accomplished by timestamping
          the message at the ingress and egress ports, taking the difference to
          determine time in the TC and adding this to the Delay Correction.
          Clients can account for the accumulated Delay Correction to determine
          a more accurate clock offset.</t>

        <t>The NTPv5 Delay Correction has the same format as the PTP
          correctionField to make it easier for manufacturers of switches and
          routers to implement NTP corrections. The format of the Correction
          Extension Field is shown in Figure <xref format="counter"
          target="correction-ext-field"/>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="correction-ext-field"
                title="Format of Correction Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF506) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                       Origin Correction                       +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        Origin Path ID         |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                       Delay Correction                        +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Delay Path ID           |     Checksum Complement       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Field Type"><vspace/>
               The type which identifies the Correction extension field (value
               TBD).</t>

            <t hangText="Length"><vspace/>
               The length of the extension field, which is 28 octets.</t>

            <t hangText="Origin Correction"><vspace/>
               A field which contains a copy of the accumulated delay
               correction from the request packet in the NTP exchange.</t>

            <t hangText="Origin Path ID"><vspace/>
               A field which contains a copy of the final path ID from the
               request packet in the NTP exchange.</t>

            <t hangText="Reserved"><vspace/>
               16 bit reserved for future specification by the IETF.
               Transmit with all zeros.</t>

            <t hangText="Delay Correction"><vspace/>
               A signed fixed-point number of nanoseconds with 48 integer
               bits and 16 binary fractional bits, which represents the current
               correction of the network delay that has accumulated for this
               packet on the path from the source to the destination. The
               format of this field is identical to the PTP correctionField.</t>

            <t hangText="Path ID"><vspace/>
               A 16-bit identification number of the path where the delay
               correction was updated.</t>

            <t hangText="Checksum Complement"><vspace/>
               A field which can be modified in order to keep the UDP
               checksum of the packet valid. This allows the UDP checksum
               to be transmitted before the Correction Field is received and
               modified. The same field is described in <xref
               target="RFC7821">RFC 7821</xref>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>A correction capable client system SHALL transmit the request with the
          Origin Correction, Origin ID, Delay Correction and Path ID fields
          filled with all zeros.</t>

        <t>Network nodes, such as switches and routers, that are capable of NTP
          corrections SHALL add the difference between the beginning of
          an NTP message retransmission and the end of the message reception to
          the received Delay Correction value, and update this field. Note that
          this time difference might be negative, for example in a cut-through
          switch. If the packet is transmitted at the same speed as it was
          received and the length of the packet does not change (e.g. due to
          adding or removing a VLAN tag), the beginning and end of the interval
          may correspond to any point of the reception and transmission as long
          as it is consistent for all forwarded packets of the same length. If
          the transmission speed or length of the packet is different, the
          beginning and end of the interval SHOULD correspond to the end of the
          reception and beginning of the transmission respectively. Both
          timestamps MUST be based on the same clock. This clock does not need
          to be synchronized as long as the frequency is accurate enough such
          that resulting time difference estimation errors are acceptable to
          the precision required by the application. The correction
          field is updated before or during the transmission of the message. It
          is a one-step transparent clock in the PTP terminology.</t>

        <t>If a network node updates the delay correction, it SHOULD also add
          the identification numbers of the incoming and outgoing port to the
          path ID. Path ID values can be used by clients to determine if the
          ntp request and response messages are likely to have traversed the
          same network path.</t>

        <t>If a network node modified any field of the extension field, it MUST
          update the checksum complement field in order to keep the current UDP
          checksum valid, or update the UDP checksum itself.</t>

        <t>The server SHALL write the received Delay Correction value in the
          origin correction field of the response message, and the received
          path ID value in the origin ID field. The server SHALL set the Delay
          Correction field and Path ID fields to all zeros</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Reference Timestamp Extension Field">
        <t>This field contains the time of the last update of the clock. It
          has a fixed length of 12 octets. In requests, that timestamp is always
          0.</t>

        <t>(Is this really needed? It was mostly unused in NTPv4.)</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="reference-timestamp-ext-field"
            title="Format of Reference Timestamp Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF507) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                      Reference Timestamp (64)                 |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Monotonic Timestamp Extension Field">

        <t>When a clock is synchronized to a time source, there is a compromise
          between time (phase) accuracy and frequency accuracy, because the
          frequency of the clock has to be adjusted to correct time errors that
          accumulate due to the frequency error (e.g. caused by changes in the
          temperature of the crystal). Faster corrections of time can minimize
          the time error, but increase the frequency error, which transfers to
          clients using that clock as a time source and increases their
          frequency and time errors. This issue can be avoided by transferring
          time and frequency separately using different clocks.</t>

        <t>The Monotonic Timestamp Extension Field contains an extra receive
          timestamp with a 32-bit epoch ID captured by a clock which
          does not have corrected phase and can better transfer frequency than
          the clock which captures the receive and transmit timestamps in the
          header. The extension field has a constant length of 16 octets. In
          requests, the counter and timestamp are always 0.</t>

        <t>The epoch ID is a random number which is changed when
          frequency transfer needs to be restarted, e.g. due to a step of the
          clock.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="monotonic-timestamp-ext-field"
            title="Format of Monotonic Timestamp Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF508) |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                            Epoch ID                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                  Monotonic Receive Timestamp (64)             |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The client can determine the frequency-transfer offset from the
          time-transfer offset and difference between the two receive
          timestamps in the response. It can use the frequency-transfer offset
          to better control the frequency of its clock, avoiding the frequency
          error in the server's time-transfer clock.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Timescale offset request">
        <t>A clients request for the offset between two indicated timescales.</t>

        <t>The reference field MUST contain the timescale identifier of
          the timescale with respect to which the client wants to know
          the offset.</t>

        <t>The target field MUST contain the timescale identifier of the
          timescale for which the client wants to know an offset.</t>

        <t>The reserved and placeholder fields MUST be set to 0
          by the client, and MUST be ignored by a server.</t>

        <t>A server which does not know either the reference or target
          timescale, or which does not know the offset between them, MUST
          ignore the timescale request.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="timescale-offset-request-ext-field"
            title="Format of Timescale Offset Request Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF509) |           Length = 16         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Reference   |    Target     |           Reserved            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                  Offset placeholder (64 bits)                 |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Timescale offset response">
        <t> The offset between two given timescales.</t>

        <t>The reference field MUST contain the timescale identifier of
          the timescale with respect to which the client wants to know
          the offset.</t>

        <t>The target field MUST contain the timescale identifier of the
          timescale for which the client wants to know an offset.</t>

        <t>The offset is given such that for a given timestamp in the
          reference timescale, the timestamp in the target timescale
          is the reference scale timestamp plus the offset. (i.e.
          target = reference + offset)</t>

        <t>The reserved bits MUST be set to 0 by the server, and MUST
          be ignored by the client.</t>

        <t>When the offset between the target and reference timescales
          varies over time, the provided offset MUST be the servers
          best approximation of this offset at the time exactly halfway
          between the receive and transmit timestamps.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="timescale-offset-response-ext-field"
            title="Format of Timescale Offset Response Extension Field">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type = [[TBD]] (draft 0xF50A) |           Length = 16         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Reference   |    Target     |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                        Offset (time64)                        |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Measurement Modes" anchor="measurement-modes">

      <t>An NTPv5 client needs four timestamps to measure the offset and delay
        of its clock relative to the server's clock:

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>T1 - client's transmit timestamp of a request</t>
          <t>T2 - server's receive timestamp of the request</t>
          <t>T3 - server's transmit timestamp of a response</t>
          <t>T4 - client's receive timestamp of the response</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The offset, delay and dispersion are calculated as:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>offset = ((T2 + T3) - (T4 + T1) + (Cd - Co)) / 2</t>
          <t>delay = |(T4 - T1) - (T3 - T2) - (Cd + Co)|</t>
          <t>dispersion = |T4 - T1| * DR</t>
        </list>

        where

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>T1, T2, T3, T4 are the receive and transmit timestamps of a
            request and response</t>
          <t>Co is the Origin Correction from the Correction Extension Field if
            present in the response and has acceptable values, zero otherwise</t>
          <t>Cd is the Delay Correction from the Correction Extension Field if
            present in the response and has acceptable values, zero otherwise</t>
          <t>DR is the client's dispersion rate</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The client can make measurements in the basic mode, or interleaved
        mode if supported on the server. In the basic mode, the transmit
        timestamp in the server response corresponds to the message which
        contains the timestamp itself. In the interleaved mode it corresponds
        to a previous response identified by the server cookie. The
        interleaved mode enables the server to provide the client with a more
        accurate transmit timestamp which is available only after the
        response was formed or sent.</t>

      <t>An example of cookies and timestamps in an NTPv5 exchange using the
        basic mode is shown in Figure <xref format="counter"
        target="basic-exchange"></xref>.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="basic-exchange"
          title="Cookies and timestamps in basic mode">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
Server   t2   t3               t6   t7              t10  t11
    -----+----+----------------+----+----------------+----+-----
        /      \              /      \              /      \
Client /        \            /        \            /        \
    --+----------+----------+----------+----------+----------+--
      t1         t4         t5         t8         t9        t12

    +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+
SC  | 0  |    | s1 |      | 0  |    | s2 |      | 0  |    | s3 |
CC  | c1 |    | c1 |      | c2 |    | c2 |      | c3 |    | c3 |
Rx  | 0  |    | t2 |      | 0  |    | t6 |      | 0  |    |t10 |
Tx  | 0  |    | t3 |      | 0  |    | t7 |      | 0  |    |t11 |
    +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>From the three exchanges in this example, the client would use the
        the following sets of timestamps:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>(t1, t2, t3, t4)</t>
          <t>(t5, t6, t7, t8)</t>
          <t>(t9, t10, t11, t12)</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>For NTPv4, the interleaved mode is described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ntp-interleaved-modes">NTP Interleaved Modes</xref>.
        The difference between the NTPv5 and NTPv4 interleaved modes is that in
        NTPv5 it is enabled with a flag and the previous transmit timestamp on
        the server is identified by the server cookie instead of the receive
        timestamp.</t>

      <t>An example of an NTPv5 exchange using the interleaved mode is shown in
        Figure <xref format="counter" target="interleaved-exchange"></xref>.
        The messages in the basic and interleaved mode are indicated with B and
        I respectively. The timestamps t3' and t11' correspond to the same
        transmissions as t3 and t11, but they may be less accurate (e.g. due to
        being captured in software before the transmission). The first
        exchange is in the basic mode followed by a second exchange in the
        interleaved mode. For the third exchange, the client request is in the
        interleaved mode, but the server response is in the basic mode, because
        the server no longer had the timestamp t7 (e.g. it was dropped to save
        timestamps for other clients using the interleaved mode).</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="interleaved-exchange"
          title="Cookies and timestamps in interleaved mode">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
Server   t2   t3               t6   t7              t10  t11
    -----+----+----------------+----+----------------+----+-----
        /      \              /      \              /      \
Client /        \            /        \            /        \
    --+----------+----------+----------+----------+----------+--
      t1         t4         t5         t8         t9        t12

Mode: B         B           I         I           I         B
    +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+
SC  | 0  |    | s1 |      | s1 |    | s2 |      | s2 |    | s3 |
CC  | c1 |    | c1 |      | c2 |    | c2 |      | c3 |    | c3 |
Rx  | 0  |    | t2 |      | 0  |    | t6 |      | 0  |    |t10 |
Tx  | 0  |    | t3'|      | 0  |    | t3 |      | 0  |    |t11'|
    +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+      +----+    +----+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>From the three exchanges in this example, the client would use the
        following sets of timestamps:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>(t1, t2, t3', t4)</t>
          <t>(t1, t2, t3, t4) or (t5, t6, t3, t4)</t>
          <t>(t9, t10, t11', t12)</t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Client Operation">
      <t>An NTPv5 client can use one or multiple servers. It has a separate
        association with each server. It makes periodic measurements of its
        offset and delay to the server. It can filter the measurements and
        compare measurements from different servers to select and combine the
        best servers for synchronization. It can adjust its clock in order to
        minimize its offset and keep the clock synchronized. These algorithms
        are not specified in this document.</t>

      <t>The polling interval can be adjusted for the network conditions and
        stability of the clock. When polling a public server on Internet, the
        client SHOULD use a polling interval of at least 64 seconds, increasing
        in normal conditions up to at least 1024 seconds to avoid excessive
        load on the server in case the implementation is used on a very large
        number of systems.</t>

      <t>Each successful measurement provides the client with an offset, delay
        and dispersion. When combined with the server's root delay and
        dispersion, it gives the client an estimate of the maximum error.</t>

      <t>On each poll, the client:

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Generates a new random cookie.</t>

          <t>Formats a request with necessary extension fields and the fields
            in the header all zero except:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Version is set to 5.</t>

              <t>Mode is set to 3.</t>

              <t>Scale is set to the timescale in which the client wants to
                operate.</t>

              <t>Poll is set to the rounded log2 value of the current client's
                polling interval in seconds.</t>

              <t>Flags are set according to the requested mode. The interleaved
                mode flag requests the server to save the transmit timestamp of
                the response and provide the transmit timestamp of a previous
                response corresponding to the server cookie (if not zero).</t>

              <t>Server cookie is set only in the interleaved mode. It is set
                to the server cookie from the last valid response, or zero if
                no such response was received yet or the transmit timestamp of
                that response would no longer be useful to the client (e.g.
                after missing too many responses).</t>

              <t>Client cookie is set to the newly generated cookie.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>Sends the request to the server to the UDP port 123 and captures a
            transmit timestamp for the packet.</t>

          <t>Waits for a valid response from the server and captures a receive
            timestamp. A valid response has version 5, mode 4, client cookie
            equal to the cookie from the request, and passes authentication if
            enabled. The client MUST ignore all invalid responses and accept at
            most one valid response.</t>

          <t>Checks whether the response is usable for synchronization of the
            clock. Such a response has a leap indicator not equal to 3, stratum
            between 0 and 16, root delay and dispersion both smaller than a
            specific value, e.g. 16 seconds, and timescale equal to the
            requested timescale. If the response is in a different timescale,
            the client can switch to the provided timescale, convert the
            timestamps if the offset between the timescales is provided or
            known, or drop the response.</t>

          <t>Saves the server's receive and transmit timestamps. If the client
            internally counts seconds using a type wider than 32 bits, it
            SHOULD expand the timestamps with the provided NTP era.</t>

          <t>Calculates the offset, delay, and dispersion as specified in
            <xref target="measurement-modes">Measurement Modes</xref>.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>A client which operates as a server for other clients MUST include the
        Reference IDs Request Extension Field in its requests in order to track
        reference IDs of its sources. If the server's set of reference IDs
        contains the client's own reference ID, it SHOULD not select the server
        for synchronization to avoid a synchronization loop. If the client
        is requesting the reference IDs in multiple chunks, it SHOULD NOT
        select the server until it received the whole set.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Server Operation">
      <t>A server receives requests on the UDP port 123. The server
        MUST support measurements in the basic mode. It MAY support the
        interleaved mode.</t>

      <t>For the basic mode the server does not need to keep any
        client-specific state. For the interleaved mode it needs to save
        transmit timestamps and be able to identify them by a cookie.</t>

      <t>The server maintains its leap indicator, stratum, root delay, and root
        dispersion:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Leap indicator MUST be 3 if the clock is not synchronized or its
            maximum error cannot be estimated with the root delay and
            dispersion. Otherwise, it MUST be 0, 1, 2, depending on whether a
            leap second is pending in the next 14 days and, if it is, whether it
            will be inserted or deleted.</t>
          <t>Stratum SHOULD be one larger than stratum of the best
            server it uses for its own synchronization.</t>
          <t>Root delay SHOULD be the best server's root delay in addition to
            the measured delay to the server.</t>
          <t>Root dispersion SHOULD be the best server's root dispersion in
            addition to an estimate of the maximum drift of its own clock since
            the last update of the clock.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The server has a randomly generated 120-bit reference ID. It MUST
        track reference IDs of its servers in order to be able to respond with
        a Reference IDs Response Extension Field.</t>

      <t>For each received request, the server:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Captures a receive timestamp.</t>

          <t>Checks the version in the request. If it is not equal to 5, it
            MUST either drop the request, or handle it according to the
            specification corresponding to the protocol version.</t>

          <t>Drops the request if the format is not valid, mode is not 3, or
            authentication fails with the MAC Extension Field or another
            authenticator which does not have a specified response for failed
            authentication. The server MUST ignore unknown extension
            fields.</t>

          <t>Server forms a response with requested extension fields and sets
            the fields in the header as follows:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Leap Indicator, Stratum, Root delay, and Root dispersion, are
                set to the current server's values.</t>

              <t>Version is set to 5.</t>

              <t>Scale is set to the client's requested timescale if it is
                supported by the server. If not, the server SHOULD respond in
                any timescale it supports.</t>

              <t>The flags are set as follows:
                <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="Unknown leap"> is set if the server does not
                    know if a leap second is pending in the next 14 days, i.e.
                    it has no source providing information about leap
                    seconds.</t>
                  <t hangText="Interleaved mode"> is set if the interleaved
                    mode is implemented, was requested, and a response in the
                    interleaved mode
                    is possible (i.e. a transmit timestamp is associated with
                    the server cookie).</t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>Era is set to the NTP era of the receive timestamp.</t>

              <t>Timescale Offset is set to the timescale-specific offset, or
                0x8000 if unknown.</t>

              <t>Server Cookie is set when the interleaved
                mode is requested and it is supported by the server, even if
                the response cannot be in the requested mode due to the request
                having an unknown or zero server cookie. The cookie
                identifies a more accurate transmit timestamp of the response,
                which can be retrieved by the client later with another
                request. The cookie generation is implementation-specific.</t>

              <t>Client Cookie is set to the Client Cookie from the
                request.</t>

              <t>Receive Timestamp is set to the server's receive timestamp of
                the request.</t>

              <t>Transmit Timestamp is set to a value which depends on the
                measurement mode. In the basic mode it is the server's current
                time when the message if formed. In the interleaved mode it is
                the transmit timestamp of the previous response identified by
                the server cookie in the request, captured at some point after
                the message was formed.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>Adds the Padding Extension field if necessary to make the length
            of the response equal to the length of the request.</t>

          <t>Drops the response if it is longer than the request to prevent
            traffic amplification.</t>

          <t>Sends the response.</t>

          <t>Saves the transmit timestamp and server cookie, if the interleaved
            mode was requested and is supported by the server.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Time Security with NTPv5">
      <t>The <xref target="RFC8915">Network Time Security</xref> mechanism uses
        the NTS-KE protocol to establish keys and negotiate the next protocol.
        NTPv5 is added as a new protocol to the Network Time Security Next
        Protocols Registry, which can be negotiated by NTPv5 clients and
        servers supporting NTS.</t>

      <t>No new NTS-KE records are specified for NTPv5. The records that were
        specified for NTPv4 (i.e. NTPv4 New Cookie, NTPv4 Server Negotiation,
        and NTPv4 Port Negotiation) are reused for NTPv5.</t>

      <t>The NTS extension fields specified for NTPv4 are compatible with
        NTPv5. No new extension fields are specified.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="NTPv5 Negotiation in NTPv4">
      <t>NTPv5 messages are not compatible with NTPv4, even if they do not
        contain any extension fields. Some widely used NTPv4 implementations are
        known to ignore the version and interpret all requests as NTPv4. Their
        responses to NTPv5 requests have a zero client cookie, which means they
        fail the client's validation and are ignored.</t>

      <t>The implementations are also known to not respond to requests
        with an unknown extension field, which prevents an NTPv4 extension
        field to be specified for NTPv5 negotiation. Instead, the reference
        timestamp field in the NTPv4 header is reused for this purpose.</t>

      <t>An NTP server which supports both NTPv4 and NTPv5 SHOULD check the
        reference timestamp in all NTPv4 client requests. If the reference
        timestamp contains the value 0x4E5450354E545035 ("NTP5NTP5" in ASCII),
        it SHOULD respond with the same reference timestamp to indicate
        it supports NTPv5.</t>

      <t>An NTP client which supports both NTPv4 and NTPv5, does not use NTS,
        and is not configured to use a particular NTP version, SHOULD start
        with NTPv4 and set the reference timestamp to 0x4e5450354e545035. If
        the server responds with the same reference timestamp, the client
        SHOULD switch to NTPv5. If no valid response is received for a number
        of requests (e.g. 8), the client SHOULD switch back to NTPv4.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Some ideas were taken from a different NTPv5 design proposed by Daniel
        Franke.</t>

      <t>The author would like to thank Doug Arnold and David Venhoek for their
        contributions and Dan Drown, Watson Ladd, Hal Murray, Kurt Roeckx, and
        Ulrich Windl for their suggestions and comments.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to create a new registry for NTPv5 Extension Field
        Types with initial entries including all entries from the <xref
        target="RFC5905">NTPv4 Extension Field Types Registry</xref> and the
        following NTPv5-specific entries:</t>

      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Field Type</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Meaning</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Padding</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>MAC</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Reference IDs Request</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Reference IDs Response</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Server Information</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Correction</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Reference Timestamp</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Monotonic Timestamp</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Timescale Offset Request</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Timescale Offset Response</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>IANA is requested to allocate the following protocol in the
        <xref target="RFC8915">Network Time Security Next Protocols
          Registry</xref>:</t>

      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Protocol ID</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Protocol Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

        <c>[[TBD]], selected by IANA from the IETF Review range</c>
        <c>Network Time Protocol version 5 (NTPv5)</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC1321;

      &RFC2119;

      &RFC8174;

      &RFC8573;

      <!-- packet timestamps &RFC8877; -->

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC5905;

      &RFC7821;

      &RFC8915;

      <!-- security requirements &RFC7384; -->

      &XLEAVE;

      <reference anchor="IEEE1588" target="https://www.ieee.org">
        <front>
          <title>
            IEEE std. 1588-2019, "IEEE Standard for a Precision Clock
            Synchronization for Networked Measurement and Control
            Systems."
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>
              Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="11" year="2019" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Bloom" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/362686.362692">
        <front>
          <title>Space/Time Trade-Offs in Hash Coding with Allowable Errors</title>
          <author surname="Bloom" fullname="Burton H. Bloom">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="6" year="1970" />
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
